<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The historye of the damnable life and deserued death of Doctor Iohn Faustus Newly imprinted, and in conuenient places, imperfect matter amended: according to the true coppy printed at Franckfort, and translated into English by P.F. Gent.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850227</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850227</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00579)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 791:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The historye of the damnable life and deserued death of Doctor Iohn Faustus Newly imprinted, and in conuenient places, imperfect matter amended: according to the true coppy printed at Franckfort, and translated into English by P.F. Gent.</title>
                  <author>P. F., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw: All-de for Edward White, and are to be solde at his shop neare the little North doore of St. Pauls Church, at the Signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The famous history of Doctor Faustus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faust, d. ca. 1540 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15414:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15414:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORYE OF The Damnable Life and deſerued Death of Doctor <hi>Iohn Fauſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newly imprinted, and in conuenient places, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect matter amended: according to the true Coppy printed at <hi>Franckfort,</hi> and tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>P. F.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw: All-de</hi> for <hi>Edward White,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neare the little North doore of St. <hi>Pauls Church,</hi> at the Signe of the Gun. 1618.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15414:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15414:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of the moſt famous Doctor <hi>Iohn Fauſtus</hi> of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> Coniurer, and Necromancer: wherein is declared many ſtrange things that he himſelfe had ſeene and done in the earth, and in the ayre, with his bringing vp, his Trauailes, Studies, and laſt end.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of his Parentage and Birth. Chap. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>OHN Fauſtus</hi> borne in the Towne of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> being in the Prouince of <hi>Weimer</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> his Father a poore husbandman, and not able well to bring him vp, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an Uncle at <hi>Wittenberg</hi> a rich man, and without iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, tooke this <hi>Fauſtus</hi> from his Father and made him his heire: inſomuch that his Father was no more troubled with him, for he remained with his vncle at <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> where he was kept at the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame City to ſtudy diuinity: but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being of a naughty minde and otherwiſe adicted, applyed not his ſtudies but tooke himſelfe to other exerciſes, the which his vncle oftentimes hearing, rebuked him for it, as <hi>Eli</hi> oftentimes rebuked his children for ſinning againſt the Lord, euen ſo this good man laboured to haue <hi>Fauſtus</hi> apply his ſtudy of diuinity, that he might come to the knowledge of God and his Lawes, but it is manifeſt that many vertuous parents haue wicked children, as <hi>Caine, Reuben, Abſolon,</hi> and ſuch like haue béene to their Parents, ſo this <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hauing godly parents, who ſéeing him to be of a toward wit were very deſirous to bring him by in thoſe vertuous ſtudies, namly of diuinity, but he gaue himſelfe ſecretly to ſtudy Necromancy &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration, inſomuch that few or none could perceiue his profeſſion.</p>
               <p>But to the purpoſe: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> continued at ſtudy in the Vniuerſitie, and was by the Rectors and ſixtéene Maiſters afterwards examined how he had profited in his ſtudies, &amp; being found by them that none for his time were able to argue with him in diuinity, or for the excellency of his wisdome to compare with him, with one conſent they made him Doctor of Diuinity. But Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> within ſhort time after he had obtained his degree, fell into ſuch fantaſies and déepe cogitations, that he was mocked of many, &amp; of the moſt part of the Students was called the <hi>Speculator:</hi> and ſomtimes he would throwe the Scriptures from him, as though he had no care of his former profeſſion: ſo that he
<pb facs="tcp:15414:3"/>began a moſt vngodly life, as hereafter more at large may appeare, for the olde prouerbe ſaith, who can hold that will away? ſo who can holde <hi>Fauſtus</hi> from the deuill that ſeekes after him with all his endeavor? For he accompanied himſelfe with diuers that were ſéene in thoſe deuilliſh artes, and that had the <hi>Chaldean, Perſian, Hebrew, Arabian,</hi> and <hi>Greeke</hi> tongues, vſing figures, characters, coniurations, incantations, with many other ceremonies belonging to thoſe internal arts, as necromancy, charmes, ſooth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ayings, witchcraft, enchantment, being delighted with their bookes, words, &amp; names ſo well, that he ſtudied day and night ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, inſomuch, that he could not abide to be called D. of Diuinity, but waxed a worldly man, and named himſelfe an Aſtrologian, and a Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician, and for ſhadow, ſometimes a Phiſition, and did great cures, namely, with hearbs, roots, waters, drinkes, receits, and clyſters. And without doubt he was paſſing wiſe, and excellent perfect in the holy Scriptures, but he that knoweth his maiſters will and doth it not, is worthy to be beaten with many ſtripes. It is written, No man can ſerue two maiſters: and, Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God: but <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> threw all this in the winde, and made his ſoule of no eſtimation: regarding more his worldly pleaſures then the ioyes to come: therfore at the day of Iudgement there is no hope of his redemption.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus began to practiſe in his deuiliſh Art, and how he coniured the deuill, making him to appeare and meet him on the morrow at his owne houſe. Chap. 2.</head>
               <p>YOU haue heard before that all <hi>Fauſtus</hi> minde was ſet to ſtudie the Artes of Necromancy and Coniuration, the which exerciſe he followed day and night: and taking to him the wings of an Eagle, thought to flye ouer the whole world, and to knowe the ſecretes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth: for his ſpeculation was ſo wonderfull, being expert in vſing his <hi>Vocabula,</hi> Figures, Characters, Coniuration, and other Ceremoniall actions, that in all haſte hée put in practiſe to bring the Deuill before him. And taking his way to a thicke Wood néere to <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> called in the Germane tongue <hi>Spiſſer Walt:</hi> that is in Engliſh the <hi>Spiſſers wood:</hi> (as <hi>Fauſtus</hi> would oftentimes boaſt of it amongſt his crue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in his iollity) hée came into the ſame wood to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards euening into a cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe way, where he made with a wand a Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the duſt, and within that many more Circles and Characters: and thus he p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt away the time vntill it was nine or tenne of the clocke in the night, then began Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to call on <hi>Mephoſtophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> the Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to charge him in the name of <hi>Belzebub,</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peace there perſonally without any long ſtay: then preſently the deuill
<pb facs="tcp:15414:3"/>began ſo great a rumor in the wood, as if heauen and earth would haue come together, with winde, that trées bowed their tops to the ground: then fell the deuill to bleat as if the whole wood had béen full of Lyons, and ſodainly about the circle ran the deuill, as if a thouſand wagons had béene running together on paued ſtones. After this, at the foure corners of the wood it thundred horribly, with ſuch lightnings, as if the whole world to his ſéeming had béene on fire. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> all this while halfe ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the deuils ſo long tarying, and doubting whether he were beſt to abide any more ſuch horrible coniurings, thought to leaue his circle and depart. whereupon the deuill made him ſuch muſicke of all ſorts, as if the Nymphes themſelues had béene in place: whereat <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued, and ſtood ſtoutly in his Circle aſpecting his purpoſe, and began againe to coniure the Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> in the name of the Prince of Deuils to appeare in his likenes: whereat ſodainely ouer his head hung honering in the ayre a mighty Dragon: then cals <hi>Fauſtus</hi> againe after his deuilliſh manner, at which there was a monſtrous crye in the wood, as if hell had béen open, and all the tormented ſoules crying to God for mercy: preſently not thrée fathame aboue his head fell a flame, in manner of a lightning, and changed it ſelfe into a Globe, yet <hi>Fauſtus</hi> feared it not, but did perſwade himſelfe that the deuill ſhould giue him his requeſt before he would leaue. Oftentimes after to his companions he would boaſt, that he had the ſtouteſt head vnder the cope of heauen at commandement: whereat they anſwered, they knew none ſtouter then the Pope, or Emperor: but Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid, the Head that is my ſeruant is aboue all on earth, and repeated certaine words out of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to make his argument good: the Prince of this world is vpon earth, and vnder heauen. Well, let vs come againe to his coniuration where we left him at his fiery Globe. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> vexed at his ſpirits ſo long tarrying, vſed his charmes, with full purpoſe not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part before he had his entent, and crying on <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> the Spirit ſodainely the globe opened, and ſprung vp in height of a man, ſo burning a time, in the end it conuerted to the ſhape of a fiery man. This pleaſant beaſt ran about the Circle a great while, and laſtly appeared in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a gray Fryer, asking <hi>Fauſtus</hi> what was his requeſt? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> commanded that the next morning at twelue of the clocke he ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his houſe: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill would in no wiſe grant: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gan againe to coniure him in the name of <hi>Belzebub,</hi> that he ſhould ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his requeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereupon the Spirit agréed, and ſo they departed each one his way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:4"/>
               <head>The conference of Doctor Fauſtus with his Spirit Mephoſtophiles the morning following at his owne houſe. Chap. 3.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hauing commanded the Spirit to be with him at his houre appointed, he came and appeared in his chamber, demanding of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> what his deſire was? then began Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anew with him to coniure him that he ſhould be obedient vnto him, and to anſwere him certaine articles, and to fulfill them in all poynts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> That the Spirit ſhould ſerue him and be obedient vnto him in all things that he asked of him from that houre till the houre of his death.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Further, any thing that he deſired of him he ſhould bring it him.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Alſo that in all <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his demands and interrogations, the ſpirit ſhould tell him nothing but that which was true.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Hereupon the Spirit anſwered, and laid his caſe foorth, that he had no ſuch power of himſelfe, vntill he had firſt giuen his Prince (that was ruler ouer him) to vnder ſtand thereof, and to know if he could obtaine ſo much of his Lord: therefore ſpeake further that &amp; may doe thy whole deſire to my prince, for it is not in my power to fulfil without his leaue. Shew me the cauſe why (ſaid <hi>Fauſtus?</hi>) the ſpirit anſwered <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thou ſhalt vnderſtand that with vs it is euen aſwell a Kingdome as with you on earth: yea, we haue our Rulers and Seruants, as I my ſelfe am one, &amp; we name our whole number the Legion: for although that <hi>Lucifer</hi> is thruſt and fallen out of heauen through his pride and high minde, yet he hath notwithſtanding a Legion of Deuills at his commandement that we call the <hi>Orientall</hi> Princes, for his power is great and infinite. Alſo there is a power in <hi>Meridie,</hi> in <hi>Septentrio,</hi> in <hi>Occidente:</hi> and for that <hi>Lucifer</hi> hath his Kingdome vnder heauen, we muſt change and giue our ſelues to men to ſerue them at their pleaſure. It is alſo certaine we haue neuer as yet opened vnto any man the truth of our dwelling, neither of our ruling, neither what ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power is, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue we giuen any man any guift, or learned him any thing, except he promiſe to be ours.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> vpon this aroſe where he ſate &amp; ſaid, I will haue my requeſt, and yet I will not be damned. The Spirit anſwered, then ſhalt thou want thy deſire, &amp; yet art thou mine notwithſtanding, if any man would detayne thee it is in vaine, for thy infidelity hath confounded thée.</p>
               <p>Hereupon ſpake <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> get thée hence from me, and take S. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentines</hi> farewell and <hi>Criſman</hi> with thée, yet I coniure thée that thou be héere at euening, and bethinke thy ſelfe of that I haue asked thée, and aske thy Princes counſaile therein. <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> the ſpirit thus
<pb facs="tcp:15414:4"/>anſwered, vaniſhed away, leauing <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in his ſtudy, where he ſate pondring with himſelfe, how he might obtaine his requeſt of the Deuill without loſſe of his ſoule: yet fully was reſolued in himſelfe rather then to want his pleaſure, to doe what the ſpirit and his Lord ſhould condition vpon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond time of the Spirit appearing to Fauſtus in his houſe and their parley. Chap. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FAuſtus</hi> continued in his deuiliſh cogitations, neuer moouing out of the place where the ſpirit left him, ſuch was his feruent lone to the deuill: the night approaching, this ſwift flying ſpirit appeared to <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> offering himſelfe with all ſubmiſſion to his ſeruice, with full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from his Prinre to doe whatſoeuer he would requeſt, if ſo be <hi>Fauſtus</hi> would promiſe to be his: this anſwere I bring thée and an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer muſt thou make by me againe, yet will I heare what is thy deſire, becauſe thou haſt ſworne me to be heare at this time. D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> gaue him this anſwere, though faintly (for his ſoules ſake) that his requeſt was none other but to become a Deuill, or at the leaſt a limbe of him, and that the ſpirit ſhould agrée vnto theſe articles as followeth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> That he might be a ſpirit in ſhape and quallity.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> That <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> ſhould be his ſeruant at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> That <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> ſhould bring him any thing, and doe for him whatſoeuer.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> That at all times he ſhould be in his houſe inuiſible to all men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept onely to himſelfe, and at his commandement to ſhew himſelfe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> Laſtly, that <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> ſhould at all times appeare at his command, in what forme or ſhape ſoeuer he would.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Vpon theſe points the ſpirit anſwered Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> that all this ſhould be granted him and fulfilled, and more: if he would agrée vnto him vpon certaine articles as followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt that Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhould giue himſelfe to the Lord <hi>Lucifer,</hi> body and ſoule.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for confirmation of the ſame he ſhould make him a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting written with his owne blood.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that he would be an enemy to all Chriſtian people.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that he would deny the Chriſtian beliefe.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, that he let not any man change his opinion, if ſo be any man ſhould goe about to diſſwade or withdraw him from if.</p>
               <p>Further, the ſpirit promiſed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to giue him certaine yeares to liue in health and pleaſure, and when ſuch yeares were expired, that
<pb facs="tcp:15414:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhould be fetched away, and if he would hold theſe articles and conditions, that then he ſhould haue all whatſoeuer his heart would with or deſire, and that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhould quickly perceiue himſelfe to be a ſpirit in all manner of actions whatſoeuer. Hereupon Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his minde was ſo inflamed, that he forgot his ſoule, and promiſed <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſtophiles</hi> to hold all things as he had mentioned them: he thought the Deuill was not blacke as they vſe to paint him, nor hell ſo hote as the people ſay, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The third parley betweene Doctor Fauſtus and Mephoſtophiles about a concluſion. Chap. 5.</head>
               <p>AFter Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had made his promiſe to the Deuill, in the morning betimes he called the ſpirit before him, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded him that he ſhould alwayes come to him like a Fryer, after the order of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> with a bell in his hand like S. <hi>Anthony,</hi> and to ring it once or twice before he appeared, that he might know of his certaine commiyg. Then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> demanded of his ſpirit what was his name. The ſpirit anſwered, my name is as thou ſayeſt, <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> and I am a Prince, but a ſeruant to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and all the circuit from <hi>Septentrio</hi> to the <hi>Meridian</hi> I rule vnder him. Euen at theſe wordes was this wicked wretch <hi>Fauſtus</hi> inflamed, to heare himſelfe to haue gotten ſo great a Potentate to ſerue him, forgetting the Lord his maker and Chriſt his Redéemer, became an enemy to all man kinde, yea worſe then the Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, whome the Poets faine to clime the hilles to make war with the Gods: not vnlike the enemy of God and his Chriſt, that for his pride was caſt into hell: ſo likewiſe <hi>Fauſtus</hi> forgot that high climbers catch the greateſt falls, and ſwéete meates haue oft the ſowreſt ſauce.</p>
               <p>After a while <hi>Fauſtus</hi> promiſed <hi>Mehoſtophiles</hi> to write and make his obligation, with full aſſurance of the articles in the chapter before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. A pittifull caſe (Chriſtian Reader) for certainly this letter or obligation was found in his houſe after his moſt lamentable end, with all the reſt of his damnable practiſes vſed in his whole life.</p>
               <p>Therefore I wiſh all Chriſtians to take example by this wicked Doctor, and to be comforted in Chriſt, contenting themſelues with that vocation, whereunto it hath pleaſed God to call them, and not to eſtéeme the vaine delight of this life, as did this vnhappy <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his ſoule to the deuil: and to confirme it the more aſſuredly, he tooke a ſmall penknife and prickt a vain in his left hand, &amp; for certainty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, were ſéene on his hand theſe wordes written, as if they had béne written with blood, <hi>O homo fuge,</hi> whereat the ſpirit vaniſhed, but
<pb facs="tcp:15414:6"/>
                  <hi>Fauſtus</hi> continued in his damnable minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus ſet his blood in a ſaucer on warme aſhes, and writ as followeth. Chap. 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Iohn Fauſtus</hi> Doctor, doe openly acknowledge with mine owne hand, to the greater force &amp; ſtrengthning of this letter, that ſith thence I began to ſtudy and ſpeculate the courſe and order of the Elements, I haue not found through the guilt that is giuen me from aboue, any ſuch learning and wiſdome, that can bring me to my deſires: and for that I finde that men are vnable to inſtruct me any further in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, now haue I Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> vnto the helliſh Prince of <hi>Orient,</hi> and his meſſenger <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> giuen both body and ſoule, vpon ſuch conditions, that they ſhall learne me, and fulfill my deſire in all thinges as they haue promiſed and vowed vnto me, with due obedience vnto me according to the articles mentioned betwéene vs.</p>
               <p>Further, I couenant and grant with them by theſe preſents, that at the end of <hi>24.</hi> yeares next enſuing the date of this preſent letter, they being expired and I in the meane time, during the ſaid yeares be ſerued of them at my will, they accompliſhing my deſires to the full in all points as we are agréed: that then I giue them all power to doe with me at their pleaſure, to rule, to ſend, fet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, or carry me or mine, be it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther body, ſoule, fleſh, blood, or goods, into their habitation, be it where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer: and hereupon, I defie God and his Chriſt, all the hoaſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and all liuing creatures that beare the ſhape of God, yea all that liues: and againe I ſay it, and it ſhall be ſo. And to the more ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this writing, I haue written it with mine owne hand and blood being in perfect memory: And hereupon, I ſubſcribe to it with my name and title, calling all the infernall, middle, and ſupreme powers to witnes of this my Letter and ſubſcription:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Fauſtus approued in the Elements and the ſpirituall Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>How Mephoſtophiles came for his writing, and in what manner he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and his ſights he ſhewed him: and how he cauſed him to keepe a coppy of his owne writings. Chap. 7.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſitting penſiue, hauing but one onely boy with him, ſodainly there appeared his Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> in likenes of a fiery man, from whome iſſued moſt horrible fiery flames, inſomuch that the boy was afraid, but being hardned by his Maſter he had him ſtand ſtill and he ſhould haue no harme: the ſpirit began to bleare as in a ſinging manner. This pretty ſport pleaſed <hi>Doctor Fauſtus</hi> well, but he would not call his Spirit into his counting-houſe, vntill he had
<pb facs="tcp:15414:7"/>ſéene more: anon was heard a ruſhing of armed men, and trampling of horſes: this ceaſing, came in a kennell of Houndes, and they chaſed a great Hart in the Hall, and there the Hart was ſlaine: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke heart, came foorth, and looked vpon the Hart, but preſently before him there was a Lyon and a Dragon together fighting ſo fiercely, that <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> thought they would haue brought downe the houſe, but the Dragon ouercame the Lyon and ſo they vaniſhed.</p>
               <p>After this came in a Pea-cocke with a Pea-hen, the cocke bruſling of his taile, and turning to the female, beat her and ſo vaniſhed. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward followed a furious Bull, that with a full fiercenes ran vpon <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> but comming néere him vaniſhed away. Afterward followed a great olde Ape, this Ape offered <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the hand, but he refuſed: ſo the Ape ran out of the hall againe. Hereupon fell a miſt in the hall, that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaw no light, but it laſted not, and ſo ſoone as it was gone, there lay before <hi>Fauſtus 2.</hi> great ſackes one full of gold the other full of ſiluer.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, was heard by <hi>Fauſtus</hi> all manner inſtruments of muſicke as Organs, Clarigolds, Lutes, Vialls, Citternes, Waights, Hornpipes, Flutes, Anomes, Harpes, and all manner other inſtruments: which ſo rauiſhed his minde, that he thought he had bin in another world, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got both body and ſoule, inſomuch that he was minded neuer to change his opinion concerning that which he had done. Hereat came <hi>Mepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophiles</hi> into the hall to <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> in apparell like vnto a Fryer to whom <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſpake, thou haſt done me a wonderfull pleaſure in ſhewing me this paſtime, if thou continue as thou haſt begun, thou ſhalt win my heart and ſoule, yea and haue it. <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> anſwered this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, I will pleaſe thée better, yea, that thou maiſt know my power and all, aske what thou wilt requeſt of me, that ſhalt thou haue, conditis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally hold thy promiſe, and giue me thy hand-writing, at which wordes the wretch thruſt foorth his hand, ſaying hold thée there haſt thou my promiſe: <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> tooke the writing, and willed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to take a coppy of it: with that the peruerſe <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being reſolute in his dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, wrote a coppy thereof, and gaue the Deuill the one, and kept in ſtore the other. Thus the ſpirit and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> were agréed and dwelt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, no doubt there was a vertuous houſe-kéeping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The manner how Fauſtus proceeded in his damnable life and of the diligent ſeruice that Mephoſtophiles vſed towards him. Chap. 8.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hauing giuen his ſoule to the Deuill, renouncing all the powers of heauen, confirming this lamentable action with his owne blood, and hauing already deliuered his writing, now into the
<pb facs="tcp:15414:7"/>Deuils hand, the which ſo puffed vp his heart, that he forgot the minde of a man, and thought himſelfe to be a ſpirit. This <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> dwelt at his vncles houſe at <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> who dyed, and bequeathed it in his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his cooſen <hi>Fauſtus. Fauſtus</hi> kept a boy with him, that was his Scholler, and vnhappy wag, called <hi>Chriſtopher Wagner,</hi> to whom this ſport and life that he faw his maiſter follow ſéemed pleaſant. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> leued the boy well, keping to make him as good or better ſéene in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilliſh exerciſes then himſelfe, and he was fellow with <hi>Mephoſtophiles:</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had no company in his houſe but himſelfe, his boy, and his ſpirit, that euer was diligent at <hi>Fauſtus</hi> command, going about the houſe cloathed like a Fryer, with a little bell in his hand ſéene of none but <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> For his victuals and other neceſſaries, <hi>Mehoſtophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> brought him at his pleaſure from the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Saltzburg:</hi> for they had many times their beſt wine ſtollen out of their ſellers by <hi>Mephoſtophiles:</hi> likewiſe their prouiſion for their owne table, ſuch meate as <hi>Fauſtus</hi> wiſhed for his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit brought him in: beſides that, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> himſelfe was become ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that when he opened his window, what fowle ſoeuer he wiſhed for, it came preſently flying into the houſe, were it neuer ſo dainty. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> and his boy went in ſumptuous apparell, the which <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſtophiles</hi> ſtole from the mercers of <hi>Norenberg, Auſpurg, Franckford</hi> and <hi>Libtzig:</hi> for it was hard for them to finde a locke to kéepe out ſuch a théefe. All their mainteinance was but ſtoine and borrowed ware: and thus they liued anodious life in the ſight of God though as yet the world were vnacquainted with their wickednes. It muſt be ſo, for their fruites be none other, as Chriſt faith in <hi>Iohn,</hi> where he calls the Deuill a théefe and a murtherer: and that found <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> for he ſtole him away both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus would haue marryed, and how the deuill had almoſt killed him for it. Chap. 9.</head>
               <p>DOrtor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> continued thus in his Epicuriſh life day and night and beléeued not that there was a God, hell, or deuill: he thought that body and ſoule dyed together: and had quite forgot Diuinity, or the immortality of his ſoule, but ſtood in his damnable hereſie day and night. And bethinking himſelfe of a wife, called <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> to counſaile, which would in no caſe agrée; demaunding of him if hée would breake the couenant made with him, or if he had forget it? Haſt not thou (quoth <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi>) ſworne thy ſelfe an enemy to God and all creatures? To this I anſwere thée thou canſt not marry,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:8"/>thou canſt not ſerue two maiſters, God &amp; my Prince: for wedlocke is a chiefe inſtitution ordained of God, and that thou haſt promiſed to deſie, as we doe all, and that haſt thou onely done, &amp; moreouer thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it with thy bloud: perſwade thy ſelfe that what thou doſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of wedlocke, it is all to thine owne delight. Therefore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> looke well about thée, and bethinke thy ſelfe better, and I with thée to change thy minde, for if thou kée not what thou haſt promiſed in thy writing, we will teare thée in peeces like the duſt vnder thy féet: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſweet <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thinke with what vnquiet life, anger, ſtrife, &amp; debate thou ſhalt liue in when thou takeſt a wife, therefore change thy minde.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was with theſe ſpeaches in diſpaire, and as all that haue forſaken the Lord can build vpon no good foundation, ſo this wretched Doctor hauing forſooke the rocke, fell into deſpaire with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, fearing if he ſhould motion Matrimony any more, that the deuill would teare him in péeces. For this time (qd. he to <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi>) I am not minded to marry. Then doeſt thou well anſweied his ſpirit. But within two houres after <hi>Fauſtus</hi> called againe his ſpirit, which came in his olde manner like a Fryer. Then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid vnto him, I am not able to reſiſt or bridle my fancy, I muſt and will haue a wife, and I pray thée giue thy conſent to it. Sodainely vpon theſe words came ſuch a whirle-winde about the place, that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thought the whole houſe would haue come downe, all the doores in the houſe flew off the hookes: after all this his houſe was full of ſmoake, and the floore couered ouer with aſhes, which when Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> perceiued, hée would haue gone vp ſtaires, and flying vp, he was taken and throwne downe into the hall that he was not able to ſtirre hand nor foote: then round about him ranne a monſtrous circle of fire, neuer ſtanding ſtill, that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> fryed as he lay, &amp; thought there to haue béene burned. Then cryed he out to his ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> for helpe, promiſing him he would liue in all things as he had vowed by his hand-writing. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon appeared vnto him an ougly deuill, ſo feare full and monſtrous to behold, that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> durſt not looke on him. The deuill ſaid, what woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou haue <hi>Fauſtus?</hi> how likeſt thou thy wedding? what minde art thou in now? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered, he had forgot his promiſe, deſiring him of pardon, and he would talke no more of ſuch things. Thou wert beſt ſo to doe, and ſo vaniſhed from him.</p>
               <p>After appeared vnto him his fryer <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> with a bell in his hand, and ſpake to <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> It is no ieſting with vs, hold thou that which thou haſt vowed, and we will performe as we haue promiſed, and more then that, thou ſhalt haue thy hearts deſire of what woman
<pb facs="tcp:15414:8"/>ſoeuer thou wilt, be ſhe aliue or dead, and ſo long as thou wilt thou ſhalt kéepe her by thée.</p>
               <p>Theſe words pleaſed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> wonderfull well, and repented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he was ſo fooliſh to wiſh himſeife marryed, that might haue any woman in the whole Cittye brought to him at his commaund: the which he practiſed and perſeuered in a long time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Queſtions put foorth by Doctor Fauſtus vnto his ſpirit Mephoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philes. Cap. 10.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> liuing in all manner of pleaſure that his heart could deſire, continuing in his amorous drifts, his delicate fare, and coſtly apparell, called on a time his <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> to him, who being come, brought with him a booke in his hand of all manner of deuilliſh and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted Arts, the which he gaue <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ſaying, hold my <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> worke now thy hearts deſire: The copy of this enchanting booke was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards found by his ſeruant <hi>Chriſtopher Wagner.</hi> Well (qd. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to his ſpirit) I haue called thée to know what thou canſt doe if I haue néed of thy helpe. Then anſwered <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> and ſaid, my Lord <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I am a flying ſpirit, yea ſo ſwift as thought can thinke to doe whatſoeuer. Héere <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid, but how came thy Lord and maiſter <hi>Lucifer</hi> to haue ſo great a fall from heauen? <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> anſwered: My Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> was a faire Angell, created of God as inmortall, and being placed in Seraphins, which are aboue the Cherubins, he would haue preſumed vnto the Throne of God, with, intent to haue thruſt God out of his ſeate. Vpon this preſumption the Lord caſt him downe head-long, and where before he was an Angell of right, now dwells in darkenes, not able to come neare his firſt place, without God ſend for him to appeare before him, as <hi>Raphiel:</hi> but vnto the lower degrée of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that haue their conuerſation with men, he may come, but not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecond degrée of heauens that is kept by the Arch-Angels, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Michaell</hi> and <hi>Gabriell,</hi> for theſe are called Angels of Gods wonders: yet are theſe farre inferiour places to that from whence my Lord and Maiſter <hi>Lucifer</hi> fell: and thus farre <hi>Fauſtus</hi> becauſe thou art one of the beloued children of my Lord <hi>Lucifer,</hi> following and féeding my minde in manner as he did his, I haue ſhortly reſolued thy requeſt, and more I will doe for thée at thy pleaſure. I thanke thée <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> (quoth <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) come let vs now goe reſt, for it is night: vpon this they left their communication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus dreamed that hee had ſcene hell in his ſleepe, and how he queſtioned with his ſpirit of matters concerning hell, with the ſpirits anſwere. Chap. 11.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:9"/>
               <p>THe night folowing after <hi>Fauſtus</hi> communication with <hi>Mephoſtophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> as concerning the fall of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> dreamed that he had ſeen part of hell, but in what maner it was, or in what place, he knew not: wherby he was much troubled in minde, and called vnto him <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> his ſpirit: ſaying vnto him, I pray thée reſolue me in this dout: what is hell, what ſubſtance is it of, in what place ſtands it, and when was it made? <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> anſwered: <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thou ſhalt knowe, that before the fall of my Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> there was no hell, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then was hell ordayned: it is no ſubſtance, but a confuſed thing, for I tell thée, that before all Elements were made, or the earth ſéene, the ſpirit of God mooued vpon the waters, and darknes was ouer all: but when God ſaid, let there be light, it was ſo at his worde, and the light was on Gods right hand, and God prayſed the light. Iudge thou fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God ſtood in the middle, the darknes was on his left hand, in the which my Lord was bound in Chaynes vntil the day of Iudgement: in this confuſed hell, is nought to finde but a ſulphuriſh fire, and ſtinking myſt or fog: Further, we deuils knowe not what ſubſtance it is of, but a confuſed thing: for as a bubble of water flyeth before the winde, ſo doth hell before the breath of God. Moreouer, we deuils know not how God hath layde the foundation of our hell, nor whereof it is, but to be ſhort <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> we know that hell hath neither bottome nor end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond queſtion put forth by Doctor Fauſtus to his ſpirit, what king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes there are in hell, how many, &amp; what were the rulers names? Chap. 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FAuſtus</hi> ſpake againe to his Spirit, ſaying: thou ſpeakeſt of wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things. I pray thée now tell me what kingdomes is there in your hell, how many are there, what are they called, and who rules them? the Spirit anſwered him, my <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> knowe that hell is, as thou wouldſt thinke with thy ſelfe an other world, in the which we haue our being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth, euen to the heauens: within the circumference whereof, are contayned tenne kingdomes, namely:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1 Lacus mortis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2 Stagnum ignis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3 Terra tenebroſa.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4 Tartarus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5 Terra obliuionis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6 Gehenna.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7 Herebus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8 Barathrum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9 Stix.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10 Acheron.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The which kingdomes are gouerned by fiue Kings, that is, <hi>Lucifer</hi> in the <hi>Orient, Belzebub</hi> in <hi>Septentrio, Belial</hi> in <hi>Meridie, Aſcaroth</hi> in the <hi>Occident,</hi> and <hi>Phlegeton</hi> in the midſt of them all: whoſe Rule and
<pb facs="tcp:15414:9"/>dominions, haue none end vntill the day of doome. And thus farre <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> haſt thou heard of our rule and Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Another queſtion put foorth by Doctor Fauſtus to his ſpirit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Lord Lucifer, with the ſorrow that Fauſtus fell afterwards into. Chap. 13.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began againe to reaſon with <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to tell him in what forme and ſhape and in what eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> was when he was in fauour with God? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his ſpirit required of him thrée dayes reſpite, which <hi>Fauſtus</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The thrée dayes being expired, <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> gaue him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> my Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> (ſo called now, for that hée was bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of the cléere light of heauen) was at the firſt an Angell of God, yea hée was ſo of God ordained, for ſhape, pompe, authority, worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and dwelling, that he farre excéeded all the other creatures of God, yea our gold and precious ſtones: and ſo illuminated, that hée farre ſurpaſſed the brightnes of the Sunne and all other Stars, where God placed him on the Cherubins: he had a Kingly office, and was alwayes before Gods ſeate, to the end he might be the more perfect in all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: But when he began to be high minded, proude, and ſo preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous that he would vſurpe the ſeate of Gods maieſty, then was he baniſhed out from amongſt the heauenly powers, ſeperated from their abiding into the manner of a fiery ſtone, that no water is able to quench but continually burneth vntill the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> when he had heard the wordes of his ſpirit began to conſider with himſelfe, hauing diuers and ſundry opinions in his head: and very penſiuely, ſaying nothing vnto his ſpirit, he went into his chamber, and laide him on his bed, recording the wordes of <hi>Mephoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philes,</hi> which ſo pierced his heart, that he fell in ſighing and great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-mentation, crying out: alas, ah woe is me what haue I done? Euen ſo ſhall it come to paſſe with me: am not I alſo a creature of Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, bearing his own Image and ſimilitude, into whom he hath brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed the ſpirit of life and immortality, vnto whome he hath made all things liuing ſubiect? but woe is me my haughty minde, proude aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtomacke, and filthy fleſh, hath brought my ſoule into perpetuall damnation, yea pride hath abuſed my vnderſtanding, inſomuch that I haue forgot my Maker, the ſpirit of God is departed from me, I haue promiſed the Deuill my ſoule: and therefore it is but a folly for me to hope for grace, but it muſt be euen with me as with <hi>Lucifer,</hi> throwne into perpetuall burning fire: ah woe is me that euer I was
<pb facs="tcp:15414:10"/>borne. In this perplexity lay this miſerable Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> hauing quite forgot his faith in Chriſt, neuer falling to repentance truly, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to attaine the grace and holy ſpirit of God againe, the which would haue béene able to haue reſiſted the ſtrong aſſaults of Sathan: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had made him a promiſe, yet he might haue remembred through true repentance, ſinners once come againe into the fauour of God; which faith the faithfull firmely hold, knowing they that kill the body are not able to hurt the ſoule: but he was in all his opinions doubtfull without faith or hope, and ſo he continued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Another diſputation betwixt Doctor Fauſtus and his Spirit, of the power of the Deuill, and his enuy to man-kinde. Chap. 14.</head>
               <p>AFter Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had a while pondred and ſorrowed with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of his wretched eſtate, he called againe <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, commanding him to tell him the iudgement, rule, power, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, tyrannie, and temptation of the deuill, and why he was moued to ſuch kinde of liuing: whereupon the ſpirit anſwered to his queſtion: that thou demaundſt of me will turne thée to no ſmall diſcontentment, therefore thou ſhouldeſt not haue deſired me of ſuch matters, for it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the ſecrets of our Kingdome, although I cannot deny to reſolue thy requeſt. Therefore know thou <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> that ſo ſoone as my Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> fell from heauen, he became a mortall enemy both to God and man, and hath vſed (as now he doth) all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of tyranny to the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, as is manifeſt by diuers examples: one falling ſuddainly dead, another hangs himſelfe, another drownes himſelfe, others ſtab themſelues, others vnlawfully diſpaire and ſo come to vtter confuſion: The firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> that was made perfect to the ſimilitude of God, was by my L. pollicy, the whole decay of man, yea <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in him was the beginning and firſt tyranny of my Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> to man: the like did he with <hi>Caine,</hi> the ſame with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> when they worſhiped ſtrange Gods and fell to whordome with ſtrange women: the like with <hi>Saul:</hi> ſo did he by the ſeauen husbands of her that after was the wife of <hi>Tobias:</hi> likewiſe <hi>Dagon</hi> our fellow brought to deſtruction <hi>50000.</hi> men wherupon the Arke of God was ſtolne: and <hi>Belial</hi> made <hi>Dauid</hi> to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his men, whereupon were ſlains <hi>60000.</hi> alſo he deceiued King <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> that worſhiped the Gods of the heathen, and there are ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits innumerable that can come by men and tempt them, driue them to ſinne, and weaken their beliefe: for we rule the hearts of Kings and Princes, ſtirring them vp to warre and blood ſhed: and to this intent doe we ſpread our ſelues throughout all the world, as the vtter enemies
<pb facs="tcp:15414:10"/>of God and his ſonne Chriſt, yea, and all that worſhip them: and that thou knoweſt by thy ſelfe <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> how we haue dealt by thée: To this ſaid <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> then thou didſt alſo beguile me: I did what I could to help thée forward: for ſo ſoone as I ſawe how thy hart did diſpiſe thy degrée taken in diuinity, &amp; didſt ſtudy to ſearch &amp; know the ſecrets of our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, then did I enter into thée, giuing thée diuers foule &amp; filthy cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>king thée forward in thine intent, perſwading thée thou couldſt neuer attaine to thy deſire, till thou hadſt the helpe of ſome deuill: and when thou waſt delighted in this, then tooke I roote in thée, &amp; ſo firmly, that thou gaueſt thy ſelfe to vs both body &amp; ſoule, which thou canſt not deny. Hereat anſwerd <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> Thou ſaiſt true, I cannot deny it: Ah woe is me moſt miſerable <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> how haue I bene deceiued? had I not had a deſire to know too much, I had not bene in this caſe: for hauing ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed the liues of the holy Saints &amp; Prophets, and therby thought to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand ſufficient heauenly matters, I thought my ſelfe not worthy to be called Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> if I ſhould not alſo know the ſecrets of hell, and be aſſociated with the furious Fiendes thereof: now therfore muſt I be rewarded accordingly. Which ſpéeches being vttred, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went very ſorowfully away from his Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus deſired againe of his Spirit, to knowe the ſecrets &amp; paynes of hell: &amp; whether thoſe damned deuils &amp; their company might euer come into the fauour &amp; loue of God againe. Chap. 15.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was euer pondering with him-ſelfe, how he might get looſe from ſo damnable an end as he had giuen himſelfe vnto both of ſoule and body: but his repentance was like to that of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> he thought his ſins greater then God could forgiue: hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his mind, he lookt vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſaw nothing therein, for his hart was ſo poſſeſſed of the deuill, that he could thinke of nought els but of hell and the paynes thereof. Wherefore in all the haſte he calleth vnto him his Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> deſiring him to tell him ſome more of the ſecrets of hell, what paynes the damned were in, and how they were tormented? &amp; whether the damned ſoules might get againe the fauour of God, and ſo be releaſed out of their torments, or not: whereupon the Spirit anſwered, My <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thou maiſt well leaue to queſtion any more of ſuch matters, for they will but diſquiet thy minde, I pray thée what meaneſt thou? thinkeſt thou through theſe thy fantaſies, to eſcape vs? No, for if thou ſhouldſt clime vp to heauen, there to hide thy ſelf, yet would I thruſt thée downe againe: for thou art mine, and thou belongſt
<pb facs="tcp:15414:11"/>vnto our ſocietie: therefore ſwéete <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thou wilt repent this thy foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh demand, except thou be content that I ſhall tell thée nothing. Quoth <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ragingly, I will know or I will not liue, wherefore diſpatch and tell me: to whom <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> anſwered, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> it is no trouble vnto me at all to tell thée, and therefore ſith thou forceſt me thereto, I will tell thée thinges to the terrour of thy ſoule, if thou wilt abide the hearing. Thou wilt haue me to tell thée of the ſecrets of Hell, and of the paines thereof: know <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that hell hath many figures, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances and names, but it cannot be named nor figured in ſuch ſort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the liuing that are damned, as it is to thoſe that are dead, and doe both ſée and féele the torments thereof: for hell is ſaid to be deadly, out of the which came neuer any to life againe but one, but he is nothing for thée to reckon vpon: hell is blood thirſty, and is neuer ſatisfied: hell is a vally into the which the damned ſoules fall: for ſo ſoone as the ſoule is out of mans body, it would gladly goe to the place from whence it came, and climeth vp aboue the higheſt hills euen to the heauens, where being by the Angells of the firſt <hi>Mobile</hi> denyed entertainment (in conſideration of their euill life ſpent on the earth) they fall into the déepeſt pit or valley which hath no bottome, into a perpetuall fire, which ſhall neuer bée quenched: for like as the Flint throwne into the water, looſeth not his vertue, neither is his fire extinguiſhed, euen ſo the helliſh fire is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable: and euen as the flint ſtone in the fire burned red hot, and conſumeth not, ſo likewiſe the damned ſoules in our helliſh fire are euer burning, but their paines neuer diminiſhing. Therefore is hell called the euerlaſting paine, in which is neither hope nor mercy. So it is called vtter darkeneſſe, in which we ſée neither the light of the Sunne, Moone, nor Starre: and were our darkeneſſe like the darkneſſe of the night, yet were there hope of mercy, but ours is perpetuall darkeneſſe, cleane exempt from the face God. Hell hath alſo a place within it cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Chaſma,</hi> out of the which iſſueth all manner of thunders, lightnings, with ſuch ſhrikings, and waylings, that oftentimes the very Deuils themſelues ſtand in feare thereof: for one while it ſendeth forth winds with excéeding ſnow, haile, and raine, congraling the water into Ice: with the which the damned are frozen, gnaſh their teeth, howle and cry, and yet cannot dye.</p>
               <p>Other whiles, it ſendeth foorth moſt horrible hot miſtes or fogges with flaſhing flames of fire and Brimſtone, wherein the ſorrowfull ſoules of the damned lye broiling in their reiterated torments: yea, <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> hell is called a priſon, wherein the damned lie continually bound: it is called <hi>Pernicies</hi> and <hi>Exitium,</hi> death, deſtruction, hurtfulneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:11"/>miſchiefe, a miſchance, a pittifull and an euill thing world without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd. We haue alſo with vs in hell a ladder, reaching of excéeding height, as though the toppe of the ſame would touch the heauens, on which the damned aſcend to ſeeke the bleſſing of God, but through their infidelity, when they are at the very higheſt degrée, they fall downe againe into their former miſeries, complaining of the heate of that vnquenchable fire: yea ſweete <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ſo muſt thou vnderſtand of hell, the while thou art ſo deſirous to know the ſecrets of our Kingdome. And marke <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> hell is the nurſe of death, the heate of all fire, the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dow of heauen and earth, the obliuion of all goodneſſe, the paines vnſpeakable, the griefes vnremouable, the dwelling of deuils, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, Serpents, Adders, Toades, Crocodiles, and all manner of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomo us and noyſome creatures: the puddle of ſinne, the ſtinking fogge aſcending from the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gian Lake, brimſtome, pitch, and all manner of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane mettals, the perpetuall and vnquenchable fire, the end of whoſe miſeries was neuer purpoſed by God: yea, yea, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thou ſaieſt I ſhall, I muſt, nay I will tell thée the ſecrets of our kingdome, for thou buyeſt it dearely, and thou muſt and ſhalt be pertaker of our torments, that (as the Lord God ſaid) neuer ſhall ceaſe: for Hell, the womans belly, and the earth, are neuer ſatisfied: there ſhalt thou abide horrible torments, trembling, gnaſhing of téeth, houling, crying, burning, frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, melting, ſwiming in a laborinth of miſeries, ſcalding, ſmoaking in thine eyes, ſtinking in thy noſe, horſenes of thy ſpéech, deafenes of thine eares, trembling of thine handes, biting thine owne tongue with paine, thy heart cruſhed as in a preſſe, thy bones broken, the diuels toſſing firebrands vpon thée, yea thy whole carcaſſe toſſed vpon muck for is, from one deuill to another, yea <hi>Fauſtus</hi> then wilt thou wiſh for death, and he will fly from thee, thine vnſpeakable torments ſhall be euery day augmented more and more, for the greater the ſinne, the greater is the puniſhment: how likeſt thou this my <hi>Fauſtus?</hi> a reſolution anſwerable to thy requeſt.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, thou wilt haue me tell thée that which belongeth onely to God, which is, if it be poſſible for the damned to come againe in to the fauour of God, or not: why <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thou knoweſt that this is againſt thy promiſe, for what ſhouldſt thou deſire to know that, hauing alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die giuen thy ſoule to the deuill, to haue the pleaſure of this world, and to know the ſecrets of hell: therefore art thou damned, and how canſt thou then came againe to the fauour of God? Wherefore I directly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere no: for whomſoeuer GOD hath forſaken and throwne into hell, muſt there abide his wrath and indignation in that vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:15414:12"/>fire, where is no hope nor mercy to be looked for, but abiding in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall paines world without end: for euen as much it auaileth thée <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> to hope for the fauour of God againe, as <hi>Luciſer</hi> himſelfe, who indéed although he and we all haue a hope, yet it is to ſmall auaile, and taketh none effect, for out of that place God will neither heare crying nor ſighing: if he doe, thou ſhalt haue as little remorſe, as <hi>Diues, Caine,</hi> or <hi>Iudas</hi> had: what hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth the Emperour, King, Prince, Duke, Earle, Baron, Lord, Knight, Squire, or Gentleman, to cry for mercy being there? Nothing: for if on earth they would not be tyrants, and ſelfe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, rich with couetouſnes, proude with pompe, gluttons, drunkards, whoeremongers, back biters, robbers, murtherers, blaſphemers, and ſuch like, then were there ſome hope to be looked for, therefore my <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> as thou commeſt to hell with theſe quallities, thou maiſt ſay with <hi>Caine,</hi> My ſins are greater then can be forgiuen, goe hang thy ſelfe with <hi>Iudas,</hi> and laſtly, be content to ſuffer torments with <hi>Diues.</hi> Therefore know <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that the damned haue neither end nor time appointed in the which they may hope to be releaſed, for if there were any ſuch hope, that they by throwing one drop of water out of the Sea in a day vntill it were dry, or if there were an heape of Sand as high as from the earth to the heauens, that a bird carrying away but one corne in a day, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of this ſo long labour, that yet they might hope at the laſt God would haue mercy on them, they would be comforted: but now there is no hope that God once thinkes vpon them, or that their howlings ſhall euer be heard, yea ſo vnpoſſible it is for thée to hide thy ſelfe from God, as vnpoſſible for thée to remoue the Mountaines, or to empty the Sea, or to tell the drops of raine that haue fallen from heauen vntill this day, or to tell what there is moſt in the world: yea and for a Camel to goe thorough the eye of a néedle, euen ſo vnpoſſible it is for thée <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and the reſt of the damned, to come againe into the fauour of God: and thus <hi>Fauſtus</hi> haſt thou heard my laſt ſentence, and I pray thée how doſt thou like it? But know this, that I counſell thée to let me be vnmoleſted hereafter with ſuch diſputations, or elſe I will vexe thée euery limbe to thy ſmall contentment. Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> departed from his ſpirit very penſiue and ſorrowfull, laying him on his bed altogether doubtfull of the grace and fauour of God, wherefore he fell into fantaſticall cogitations: faine he would haue had his ſoule at libertie againe, but the deuill had ſo blinded him, and taken ſuch déepe roote in his heart, that he could neuer thinke to craue Gods mercy, or if by chance he had any good motion, ſtraight wayes the deuill would thruſt in a faire Lady into his chamber, which fell to kiſſing and dalliance with him, through which meanes, he threw
<pb facs="tcp:15414:12"/>his godly motion in the winde, going forward ſtill in his wicked practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to the vtter ruine both of his body and ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>Another queſtion put foorth by Doctor Fauſtus to his Spirit Mephoſtophiles of his owne eſtate. Chap. 16.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being yet deſirous to heare more ſtrange things, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his ſpirit vnto him ſaying: By <hi>Mephoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ophi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> I haue yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſute vnto thée, which I pray thée deny me not to reſolue me of: <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> (qd. the ſpirit) I am loath to reaſon with thee any further, for thou art neuer ſatisfied in thy minde but alwayes bringeſt me anew: Yet I pray thée this once (qd. <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) doe me ſo much fauour, as to tell me the truth in this matter, and hereafter I will be no more ſo earneſt with thée: the ſpirit was altogether againſt it, but yet once more he would abide him: well (ſaid the ſpirt to <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) what demandeſt thou of me? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid, I would gladly know of thée, if thou wert a man in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e as I am, what wouldſt thou doe to pleaſe both God and man? whereat the ſpirit ſmiled, ſaying: My <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> if I were a man as thou art, and that God had adorned me with thoſe guifts of nature, as thou once hadſt, euen ſo long as the breath of God were by, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mée, would I humble my ſelfe vnto his Maieſtie, endeauouring in all that I could to kéepe his commandements, praiſe him and glorifie him, that I might continue in his fauour, ſo were I ſure to enioy the eternall ioy and felicitie of his kingdome: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid, but that I haue not done, No, thou ſaiſt true (qd. <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi>) thou haſt not done it, but thou haſt denyed the Lord thy maker, which gaue thée the breath of life, ſpéech, hearing, ſight, and all other thy reaſonable ſences, that thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vnderſtand his will and pleaſure, to liue to the glory and honour of his name, and to the aduancement of thy body and ſoule: him I ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy maker haſt thou denyed and defied, yea, wickedly thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed that excellent guift of thy vnderſtanding, and giuen thy ſoule to the deuill: therfore giue none the blame but thine owne ſelf, will, thy proud and aſpiring minde, which hath brought thée into the wrath of God and vtter damnation. This is moſt true (qd. <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) but tell me <hi>Mepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophiles,</hi> wouldſt thou be in my caſe as I am now? yea ſaith the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (and with that fetcht a great ſigh) for yet would I ſo humble my ſelfe that I would win the fauour of God, Then (ſaid D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) it were time inough for me, if I amended. True (ſaid <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi>) if it were not for thy great ſinnes, which are ſo odious and deteſtable in the ſight of God that it is too late for thée, for the wrath of God reſteth vpon thée. Leaue off (qd. <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) and tell me my queſtion to my greater comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:13"/>
               <head>Here followeth the ſecond part of Doctor Fauſtus his life, and practiſes vntill his end. Chap. 17.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hauing receiued deniall of his ſpirit, to be reſolued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more in ſuch like queſtions propounded: forgot all good workes, and fell to be a Kalender-maker by the helpe of his ſpirit, and alſo u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort time to be a good Aſtronomeror Aſtrologian: he had learned ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly of his Spirit the courſe of the Sunne, Moone, and Starres, that he had the moſt famous name of all the Mathem atiques that liued in his time, as may well appeare by his workes dedicated vnto ſundry Dukes and Lords: for be did nothing without the aduice of his ſpirit, which learned him to preſage of matters to come, which haue come to paſſe ſince his death. The like praiſe won he with his Kalenders and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacks making, for when he preſaged of any thing, operation, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the weather or Elements: as winde, rame, fogs, ſnow, haile, moyſt, dry, warme, colde, thunder, lightning it fell ſo duely out, as if an Angell of heauen had forewarned it. He did not, like the vnskilfull Aſtronomers of our time, that ſet in Winter, cold, moyſt airy, froſty: and in the Dog-dayes, hot, dry, thunder, fire, and ſuch like, but he ſet in all his workes, day and haure when, where, and how it ſhould dappen. If any wonderfull thing were at hand, as mortalitie, famine, plague, or warres, he would ſet the time and place, in true and iuſt order, when it ſhould come to paſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>A queſtion put forth by Doctor Fauſtus to his Spirit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Aſtronomy. Chap. 18.</head>
               <p>NOw <hi>Fauſtus</hi> falling to practice and making his Progneſtications, he was doutfull in many points: wherefore he called vnto him <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſtophiles</hi> his Spirit, ſaying: I finde the ground of this ſcience very difficult to attaine vnto: for when that I conferre <hi>Aſtronomia,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologia,</hi> as the Mathematicians, and ancient writers haue left in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye, I finde them to barry, and very much to diſagree: wherefore I pray thée to teach me the truth in this matter: to whome his ſpirit an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thou ſhalt knowe, that the practicioners or ſpeculators, or at leaſt the firſt inuenters of theſe Artes, haue done nothing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues certaine, whereupon thou maiſt attaine to the true prognoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or preſaging of things concerning the heauens: or of the influence of the planets: for if by chaunce ſome one Mathematician or Aſtronomer hath left behinde him any thing worthy of memory, they haue ſo blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it with <hi>Enigmaticall</hi> wordes, blinde Characters, and ſuch obſcure ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, that it is impoſſible for an earthly man to attaine to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, without the ayde of ſome ſpirit, or els the ſpeciall guift of
<pb facs="tcp:15414:13"/>God, for ſuch are the hidden works of God from men, yet doe we ſpirits that die and fléete in all Elements, know ſuch, and there is nothing to be done, or by the heauens pretended, but we know it, except onely the day of Doome. Wherefore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> learne of me, I will teach thée the courſe &amp; recourſe of ♄ ♃ ♀. ☉ ☿ and ☾. the cauſe of winter and ſummer, the exaltation and declination of the Sunne, and Ecclipſe of the Moone, the diſtance and height of the Poles, and euery fixed ſtarre, the nature and operation of the Elements, fire, ayre, water and earth, and all that is contained in them, yea herein there is nothing hidden from me, but onely the filthy eſſence which once thou hadſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> at liberty, but now <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thou haſt loſt it paſt recouery: wherefore leauing that which wil not be again had, learn now of me to make thunder, lightning, haile, ſnow and raine, the cloudes to rent, the earth and craggy rocks to ſhake and ſplit in ſunder: the Seas to ſwell &amp; rore, and ouer-run their markes: knoweſt not thou that the déeper the Sunne ſhines the hotter he pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? ſo the more thy Art is famous whileſt thou art héere, the greater ſhall be thy name when thou art gone. Knoweſt not thou that the earth is frozen, cold and dry: the water running, cold, and moiſt, the ayre fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hot and moiſt: the fire conſuming hot and dry? Yea <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ſo muſt thy heart be inflamed like the fire to mount on high: learne <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> to flie like my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as ſwift as thought from one kingdome to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſit at Princes tables, to eate their dain tieſt fare, to haue thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Ladyes, wiues and concubines, to vſe all their iewels and coſtly robes as thinges belonging vnto thée, and not vnto them: learne of me <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to runne through walles, doores, and gates of ſtone and yron, to créepe into the earth like a Worme: to ſwim in the water like a fiſh, to fly in the ayre like a Bird, and to liue and nouriſh thy ſelfe in the fire like a Salamander, ſo ſhalt thou be famous, renowned, farre ſpoken of, and extolled for thy skill: going on kniues not hurting thy féete, carrying fire in thy boſome and not burning thy ſhirt, ſéeing through the heauens as through a Chriſtall, wherein is placed the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, with all the reſt of the preſaging Comets, the whole circuit of the world from the Eaſt to the Weſt, North and South: there ſhalt thou know <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> wherefore the fiery ſphere aboue, and the ſignes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack doth not burne and conſume the whole face of the earth, being hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by placing the two moiſt elements between thein, the airy cloudes and the wauering wanes of water: yea <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I will learne thee the ſecrets of nature, what the cauſe is that the ſun in ſommer being at the higheſt, giueth all his heate downewards on the earth: and being in Winter at the loweſt, giueth all his heate vpward into the Heauens,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:14"/>that the ſnow ſhould be of ſo great vertue as the honny, and the Lady <hi>Saturnia</hi> in <hi>Occulto,</hi> more hotter then the Sun in <hi>Manifeſto.</hi> Come on my <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I will make thée as perfect in theſe thinges as my ſelfe, I will learne thée to goe inuiſible, to finde out the mines of gold and ſiluer: the fodines of precions ſtones, as the Carbuncle, the Diamond, Saphir, Emerald, Ruby, Topas, Iacinet, Granat, Iaſpis, Amachiſt: vſe all theſe at thy pleaſure, take thy hearts deſire, thy time <hi>Fauſtus</hi> weareth away, then why wilt thou not take thy pleaſure of the world? Come vp we will goe vnto Kinges at their owne Courts and at their moſt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous banquets be their gueſts: if willingly they inuite vs not, then perforce we will ſerue our owne turne with their beſt meate, and dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt wine: Agréed qd. <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> but let me pauſe a while vpon this thou haſt euen now declared vnto me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus fell into deſpaire with himſelfe, for hauing put foorth a queſtion vnto his ſpirit, they fell at variance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the rout of Deuils appeared vnto him, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him ſharply. Chap. 19.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> reuoluing with himſelfe the ſpéeches of his ſpirit, he became ſo woful and ſorrowfull in his cogitations, that he thought himſelfe already frying in the hotteſt flames of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; lying in this muſe, ſuddenly there appeared vnto him his ſpirit, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>unding what thing ſo grieued and troubled his conſcience? where at Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> gaue no anſwer: yet the ſpirit very earneſtly lay vpon him to know the cauſe, and if it were poſſible, he would finde remedy for his griefe and eaſe him of his ſorrowes. To whom <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered, I haue taken thee vnto me as a ſeruant to do me ſeruice, and thy ſeruice will be very deare vnto me: yet I cannot haue any diligence of thée further then thou liſt thy ſelfe, neither doeſt thou in any thing as it becommeth thée. The ſpirit replyed. My <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thou knoweſt that I was neuer againſt thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements as yet, but ready to ſerue and reſolue thy queſtions, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am not bound vnto thée in ſuch reſpects as concerne the hurt of our Kingdome, yet was I alwayes willing to anſwer thée and ſo am ſtill: therefore my <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſay on boldly, what is thy will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? At which words the ſpirit ſtole away the heart of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> who ſpake in this ſort, <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> tell me how and after what ſort God made the world, and all the creatures in them, and why man was made after the Image of God? the ſpirit hearing this: anſwered, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thou knoweſt that all this is in vaine for thée to aske, I know that thou art ſory for that thou haſt done, but it auaileth thée not, for I will
<pb facs="tcp:15414:14"/>thouſand péeces if thou change not thine opinions, and hereat he vaniſhed away. Whereat <hi>Fauſtus</hi> all ſorrowfull for that he had put forth ſuch a queſtion, fell to wéeping and to howling bitterly, not for his ſinnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, but that the Deuill was departed from him ſo ſodainly and in ſuch a rage. And being in this perplexity, he was ſuddainly taken in ſuch an extreame colde, as if he ſhould haue frozen in the place where he ſate, in which the greateſt deuill in hell appeared vnto him, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his hideous and infernall company in moſt vglieſt ſhapes, that it was vnpoſſible to thinke vpon, and trauerſing the chamber round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout where <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſate, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thought to himſelfe, now are they come for me though my time be not come, and that becauſe I haue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſuch queſtions of my ſeruant <hi>Mephoſtophiles:</hi> at whoſe cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the chiefeſt deuill which was the Lord, vnto whome he gaue his ſoule, that was <hi>Lucifer,</hi> ſpake in this ſort: <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I haue ſéene thy thoughts, which are not as thou haſt vowed vnto me, by vertue of this Letter, and ſhewed him the Obligation which he had written with his owne blood, wherefore I am come to viſite thée, and to ſhew thée ſome of our helliſh paſtimes, in hope that will drawe and confirme thy minde a little more ſtedfaſt vnto vs. Content quoth <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> goe too, let me ſée what paſtime you can make. At which wordes the great deuill in his likenes ſate him downe by <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> commaunding the reſt of the deuils to appeare in their forme, as if they were in hell: Firſt entred <hi>Belial</hi> in forme of a Beare with curled blacke haire to the ground, his eares ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpright: within the eare was as red as blood, out of which iſſued flames of fire, his téeth were at leaſt a foote long, as white as ſnow, with a taile thrée elles long (at the leaſt) hauing two winges one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde each arme, and thus one after another they appeared to <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in forme as they were in hell: <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelfe ſate in manner of a man all hairy, but of a browne colour like a Squirrell curied, and his taile tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpward on his backe as the Squirrels vſe, I thinke he could crack nuts too, like a Squirrell. After him came <hi>Belzebub</hi> in curled haire of a horſe-fleſh colour, his head like the head of a Bul, with a mighty paire of hornes, and two long eares downe to the ground, and two wings on his backe with pricking things like thornes: out of his wings iſſued flames of fire, his taile was like a Cowes. Then came <hi>Aſtoroth</hi> in forme of a worme going vpright on his taile, &amp; had no féete, but a taile like a Slow-worme: vnder his chappes grew two ſhort hands, and his barke was cole-blacke, his belly thicke in the middle, yellow like golde, hauing many briſtles on his backe like a Hedge-heg. After him came <hi>Chania<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta,</hi> being white and gray mixed, excéeding curled and hairy, he had
<pb facs="tcp:15414:15"/>a head like the head of an Aſſe, and a taile like a Cat, and clawes like an Oxe, lacking nothing of an ell broad. Then came <hi>Anobis,</hi> this deuill had a head like a dog, white and blacke haire, in ſhape like a hog, ſauing that he had but two féete, one vnder his threate, the other at his taile, he was foure elles long, with hanging cares like a blood-hound. After him came <hi>Dithican,</hi> he was a ſhort théefe, in forme of a Feaſant, with ſhining feathers, and toure féete, his necke was grée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, his body re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and his féete blacke. The laſt was called <hi>Brachus,</hi> with foure ſhort féete like a Hedge hog, yellow and gréene, the vpper ſide of his body was browne, and the belly like blew flames of fire: the taile red like the taile of a Monkey. The reſt of the deuils were in forme of vnſenſible beaſts, as Swine, Harts Beares, Woolfes, Apes, Buffes, Goates, Antlops, Elephants, Dragons, Horſes, Aſſes, Lyons, Cats, Snakes, Loades, and all manner of vgly odious Serpents and wormes: yet came in ſuch ſort, that euery one at his entry into the Hall, made their reuerence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Lucifer</hi> and ſo tooke their places, ſtanding in order as they came, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they had filled the whole Hall, wherewith ſodainly fell a moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thunder-clap, that the houſe ſhooke as though it would haue fallen to the ground, vpon which euery monſter had a muck forke in his hand, holding them towards <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> as though they would haue run at tilt at him: which when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> perceiued, he thought vpon the wordes of <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> when he told him how the ſoules in hell were tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted being caſt from deuill to deuill vpon mucke-forkes, he thought verily to haue béene tormented there of them in like ſort. But <hi>Lucifer</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his thought, ſpake to him, My <hi>Fauſtus</hi> how likeſt thou this crew of mine? quoth <hi>Fauſtus</hi> why came not you in another manner of ſhape? <hi>Lucifer</hi> replyed, we cannot change our helliſh forme, we haue ſhewed our ſelues héere, as we are there: yet can we blinde mens eyes in ſuch ſort, that when we will we repaire vnto them, as if we were men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of light, although our dwelling be in darkenes. Then ſaid <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I like not ſo many of you together, whereupon <hi>Lucifer</hi> commanded them to depart, except <hi>7.</hi> of the principali, forthwith they preſently vaniſhed, which <hi>Fauſtus</hi> perceiuing, he was ſomewhat better comforted, and ſpake to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> where is my ſeruant <hi>Mephoſtophiles?</hi> let me ſee if he can doe the like, whereupon came a fierce Dragon flying, and ſpitting fire round about the houſe, and comming towards <hi>Lucifer,</hi> made reuerence, and then changed himſelfe to the forme of a Frier ſaying <hi>Fauſtus</hi> what wilt thou? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid, I will that thou teach me to transforme my ſelfe in like ſort as thou and the reſt haue done: then <hi>Lucifer</hi> put foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h his paw and gaue <hi>Fauſtus</hi> a booke, ſaying, hold, doe what thou wilt, which hée
<pb facs="tcp:15414:15"/>looking vpon, ſtraight wayes changed himſelfe into a hogge, then into a Worme, then into a Dragon, and finding this for his purpoſe, it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him well. Quoth he to <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and how commeth it that ſo many filthy formes are in the world? <hi>Lucifer</hi> anſwered, they are ordained of God as plagues vnto men, and ſo ſhalt thou be plagued (quoth he) whers vpon came Scorpions, Waſpes, Emits, Bées, and Enats, which fell to ſtinging and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng him, and all the whole houſe was f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>led with a moſt horrible ſtinking fogge, inſomuch that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaw nothing, but ſtill was tormented: wherefore he cryed for helpe, ſaying, <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> my faithfull ſeruant where art thou? helpe, helpe I pray thée: hereat the ſpirit anſwering nothing, but <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelfe ſaid, ho, ho, ho <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> how likeſt thou the creation of the world? and incontinent it wes cleare againe, and the diuels and all the filthy cattell were vaniſhed, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was left alone, ſéeing nothing, but hearing the ſwéeteſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke that euer he heard before, at which he was ſo rauiſhed with delight, that he forgot his feares hée was in before, and it repented him that he had ſéene no more of their paſtime.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus deſired to ſee hell, and of the manner how he was vſed therein. Chap. 20.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> bethinking how his time went away, and how hee had ſpent eight yeares thereof, he ment to ſpend the reſt to his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contentment, intending quite to forget any ſuch motions as might offend the deuill any more: wherefore on a time he called his Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> and ſaid vnto him, bring thou hither vnto mee thy Lord <hi>Lucifer</hi> or <hi>Behall:</hi> he brought him (notwithſtanding) one that was called <hi>Belzebub,</hi> the which asked <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his pleaſure? Quoth <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I would know of thoe if I may ſee hell and take a view there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? That thou ſhalt ſaid the diuell, and at midnight I will fetch thée. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, night being come, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> awaited very diligently for the comming of the diuell to fetch him, and thinking that he tarryed all too long, hee went to the window, where he pulled open a cazement, and looking into the Element, he ſaw a cloude in the North, more blacke, darker and obſcure, then all the reſt of the skie, from whence the winde blew moſt horrible right into <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his chamber, and filled the whole houſe with ſmoke, that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was almoſt ſmothered: hereat fell an excéeding thunder clap, and withall came a great rugged blacke Beare all cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>led and vpon his backe a chaire of beaten gold, and ſpake to <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ſaying, ſit vp and away with me: and Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> that had ſo long abode the ſmoake, wiſht rather to be in hell then there, got on the diuell, and ſo they went together. But marke how the diuell
<pb facs="tcp:15414:16"/>blinded him, and made him beléeue they carryed him into hell, for he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed him into the ayre, where <hi>Fauſtus</hi> fell into a ſound ſléepe, as if he had ſate in a warme water or bath: at laſt they came to a place which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth continually with flaſhing flames of fire and brimſtone: where aut iſſued an excéeding mighty clap of thunder, with ſo horrible a noiſe, that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> awaked: but the deuill went foorth on his way, and carried <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> thereinto, yet notwithſtanding howſoeuer it burnt. D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſelf no more heate, then as it were the glimps of the Sunne in May, there heard he all manner of muſicke to welcome him, but ſaw none playing on them, it pleaſed him well but he durſt not aske, for he was forbidden it before. To méete the deuill and the gueſt that came with him, came <hi>3.</hi> other vgly deuils, the which ranne backe againe before the Beare, to make the way, againſt whome there came running an excéeding great Hart which would haue thruſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> out of his chaire, but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by the other thrée deuils, the Hart was put to the repulſe: thence going on their way <hi>Fauſtus</hi> looked, and beholde, there was nothing but Snakes and all manner of venemous beaſts about him, which were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding great, vnto the which Snakes came many Storkes and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp all the whole multitude of Snakes, that they left not one: which when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaw, he maruailed greatly, but procéeding further on their helliſh dayage, there came foorth of an bollow cliffe an excéeding great flying Bull, the which with ſuch a force hit <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his chaire with his head and hornes, that he turned <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and his Beare ouer and ouer, ſo that the Beare vaniſhed away, whereat <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began to cry, oh, woe is me that euer I came héere: for he thought there to haue béene begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of the deuill, and to make his end before his time appointed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned of the deuill, but ſhortly after came vnto him amonſtrous Ape, kidding <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to be of good chéere and ſaid, get vpon me: all the fire in hell ſeemed to <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to haue beene put out, whereupon followed a monſtrous thicke fogge, that he ſaw nothing, but ſhortly it ſeemed to him to waxe cleere, where he ſaw two great Dragons faſined vnto a Waggon, into the which the Ape aſcended and ſet <hi>Fauſtus</hi> therein, foorth ſlew the Dragons into an exceeding darke cloude. where <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaw neither Dragon nor Chariot wherein he ſate, and ſuch were the cries of tormented ſoules, with mighty thunder claps and flaſhing lightnings about his eares, that poore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhooke for feare. Vpon this came they to a water, ſtincking and filthy, thicke like mudde, into the which ranne the Dragon, ſincking vnder with waggon and all, but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> felt no water, but as it were a ſmall miſt, ſauing that the waues beate ſo ſore vpon him, that he ſaw nothing vnder and ouer him but onely water,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:16"/>in the which he leſt his Dragons, Ape, and Waggon: and ſinking yet déeper and déeper, he came at laſt as it were vpon a high Rocke, where the waters parted and left him thereon: but when the water was gone, it ſéemed to him he ſhould there haue ended his life, for he ſaw no way but death: the Rocke was as high from the bottome as heauen is from the earth, there ſate he, ſéeing nor hearing any man, and looked euer vpon the Rocke: at length he ſawe a little hole, out of the which iſſued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re: thought he, how ſhall I now doe? I am forſaken of the deuils, and they that brought me hither, héer muſt I either fall to the bottome, or burns in the fire, or ſit ſtill in diſpaire: with that in his madnes he gaue a skip into the fiery hole, ſaying: holde you infernall hags, take here this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as my laſt end, that which I iuſtly haue deſerued: vpon this he was entred, and finding himſelfe as yet vnburned or touched of that fire, he was the beter appaied, but there was ſo great a noiſe, as he neuer heard the like before, it paſſed all the thunder that euer he had heard, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe further to the bottome of the rocke, he ſaw a fire, wherein were many worthy and noble perſonages, as Emperors, Kings, Dukes and Lords, and many thouſands more of tormented ſoules, at the edge of which fire ran a moſt pleaſant, cleare, and cold water to behold, into the which many formented ſoules ſprang out of the fire to coole them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but being ſo fréezing cold, they were conſtrained to returne again into the fire, and thus wearied themſelues, &amp; ſpent their endles torments out of one laborinth into another, one while in heate, another while in colde: but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſtanding héere all this while gazing on them that were thus tormented, he ſawe one leaping out of the fire and ſcriching horribly, whome he thought to haue knowne, wherefore he would faine haue ſpoken vnto him, but remembring that he was forbidden, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained ſpeaking. Then this deuill that brought him in, came to him againe in likenes of a Beare, with the chaire on his backe, and bad him ſit vp for it is time to depart: ſo <hi>Fauſtus</hi> got vp, and the deuill carryed him out into the ayre, where he had ſo ſwéet muſicke that he fell a ſléep by the way. His boy <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> being all this while at home, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his maſter ſo long, thought his maiſter would haue tarryed and dwelt with the deuill foreuer: but whilſt his boy was in theſe cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his maiſter came home, for the deuill brought him home faſt aſléepe as he ſate in the chaire, and threw him on his bed, where (being thus leſt of the deuill) he lay vntill day. When he awaked, he was amazed, like a man that had béene in a darke dungeon: muſing with himſelfe if it were true or falſe that he had ſéene Hell, or whether he was blinded or not, but he rather perſwaded himſelfe that he had béene there then
<pb facs="tcp:15414:17"/>otherwiſe, becauſe he had ſéene ſuch wonderfull thinges: wherefore he moſt carefully tooke pen and inke, and wrote thoſe thinges in order as he had ſéene: the which writing was afterwards found by his boy in his ſtudy: which afterwards was publiſhed to the whole Citty of <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg</hi> in print, for example to all Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus was carryed through the ayre vp to the heauen to ſee the whole world, and how the Skie and Planets ruled, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the which he wrote a letter to his friend of the ſame to Liptzig, and how he went about the world in eight dayes. Chap. 19.</head>
               <p>THis Letter was found by a frée man and Cittizen of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> written with his own hand, and ſent to his friend at <hi>Liptzig</hi> a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, named <hi>Ioue Victory:</hi> the contents of which were as followeth: Amongſt other things, (my louing friend and brother) I remember yet the former friendſhip had together, when we were ſchoole fellowes and Students in the Vniuerſitie at <hi>Wittenberg</hi> whereas you firſt ſtudied Phyſick, Aſtronomy, Aſtrology, Grometry, and Coſmographie, I to the contrary (you know) ſtudied Diuinity, notwithſtanding now in any of your owne ſtudies I am ſeen (I am perſwaded) further then your ſelfe: for ſithence I began I haue neuer e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red, for (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight I ſpeake it without affecting my own praiſe) my Kalenders, and other practiſes haue not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the commendations of the common ſort, but alſo of the chiefeſt Lords and Nobles of this our Dutch nation becauſe (which is chiefly to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) I write and preſage of matters to come w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all accord and fall out ſo right, as if they had bin already ſéne b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore. And for that (my beloued <hi>Victory</hi>) you write to know my voyage which I made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens, the which (as you certifie me you haue had ſome ſuſpition of) although you parrly perſwaded your ſelfe, that it is a thing vnpoſſible, no matter for that, it is as it is, &amp; let it be as it will, once it was done in ſuch ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner as now according vnto your requeſt I giue you héere to vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>I being once laide on my bed, and could not ſléepe for thinking on my Kalender and practiſe. I maruailed with my ſelfe how it were poſſible that the Firmament ſhould be knowne and ſo largely written of men, or whether they write true or falſe, by their owne opinions, or ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or by due obſeruations and true courſe of the heauens. Behold, I thought my houſe would haue bene blowne downe, ſo that all my doores and cheſts flew open, whereat I was not a little aſtonied, for withall I heard a groaning voyce, which ſaid, get vp, the deſire of thy heart, minde, and thought ſhalt thou ſée, at the which I anſwered, what my heart deſireth, that would I faine ſée, and to make proofe, if I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:15414:17"/>ſée I will away with thée. Why then (quoth he) looke out at thy win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, their commeth a meſſenger for thée, that did I, and behold there ſtood a Waggon, with two Dragons before it, to draw the ſame, and all the Waggon was of a light burning fire, and for that the Moone ſhone, I was the willinger at that time to depart, but the voice ſpake againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſir vp and let vs away: I will (ſaid I) goe with thée, but vpon this condition, that I may aske after all thinges that I ſée, heare, or thinke on: the voice anſwered, I am content for this time. Hereupon I got me into the Waggon, ſo that the Dragons carried me vpright into the ayre.</p>
               <p>The Waggon had alſo <hi>4.</hi> whéeles, the which ratled ſo, and made ſuch a noiſe, as if we had all this while béene running on the ſtones: &amp; round about vs flew out flames of fire, and the higher that I came, the more the earth ſéemed to be darkened, ſo that me thought I came out of a dungeon: and looking downe from heauen, behold <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> my Spirit and ſeruant was behind me, and when he perceiued that I ſaw him, he came and ſate by me, to whome I ſaid, I pray thée <hi>Mepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophiles</hi> whether ſhal I goe now? Let not that trouble thy mind, ſaid he, and yet they carryed vs higher vp, And now will I tell thée (good friend and ſchoole-fellow) what thinges I haue ſéene and prooued, for on the Tueſday went I out, and on Tueſday ſeauen night following, I came home againe, that is eight dayes, in which time I ſlept not, no not one winke came in mine eyes: and we went inniſible of any man: and as the day began to appeare, after my firſt nights iourney, I ſaid to my Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> I pray thée how farre haue we now ridden, I am ſure thou knoweſt: for me thinkes that we are ridden excéeding farre, the world ſéemeth ſo little: <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> anſwered mee, my <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> beléeue me that from the place from whence thou cameſt, vnto this place where we are now, is already forty ſeauen leagues right in height, and as the day increaſed, I looked downe vpon the world. <hi>Aſia, Europa,</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> I had a ſight of: and being ſo high, qd. I to my Spirit, tell me now how theſe Kingdomes lie, and what they are called: the which he denied not, ſaying, ſee this on our left hand is <hi>Hungaria,</hi> this is alſo <hi>Pruſſia</hi> on our left hand, and <hi>Poland, Muſcouia, Tartaceleſia, Bohemia, Saxony:</hi> and héere on our right hand, <hi>Spaine, Portugall, France, England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> then right on before vs lie the kingdoms of <hi>Perſia India, Arabia,</hi> the King of <hi>Althar,</hi> and the great <hi>Cham:</hi> now are we come to <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and are right ouer the towne of <hi>Weim in Auſtria,</hi> and ere long will be at <hi>Conſtantinople, Tripolie,</hi> and <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and after will we pierce the frozen Zone, and ſhortly touch the
<pb facs="tcp:15414:18"/>Horizon, and the zenith of <hi>Wittenberg.</hi> There looked I on the <hi>Ocean</hi> Sea, and beheld a great many Shippes, and Gallyes ready to the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile one againſt another: and thus I ſpent my iourney: now caſt I my eyes héere, now there, towards South, North, Eaſt, and Weſt, I haue béene in one place where it rained and hailed, and in another where the Sun ſhone excellent faire, and ſo I thinke that I ſaw moſt thinges in and about the world, with great admiration, that in one place it tained, and in another haile and ſnow: on this ſide, the Sun ſhone bright, ſome hills couered with ſnow neuer conſuming, other were ſo hot that graſſe and trées were burned and conſumed therewith. Then looked I vp to the heauens, and behold they went ſo ſwift, that I thought they would haue ſprung in thouſands. Likewiſe it was ſo cléere and ſo hot, that I could not long gaze into it, it ſo dimmed my ſight: and had not my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> couered me as it were with a ſhadowing cloude, I had béene burnt with the extreame heate thereof: for the Sky the which we behold héere when we looke vp from the earth, is ſo faſt and thicke as a wall, cléere and ſhining bright as Chriſtall, in the which is placed the Sunne, which caſteth foorth his raies and beames ouer the vniuerſal world, to the vttermoſt confines of the earth. But we thinke that the ſun is very little: no, it is altogether as big as the world: Indéed the body ſubſtantiall is but little in compas, but the raies or ſtreames that it caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth, by reaſon of the thing wherein it is placed, maketh him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and ſhew himſelfe ouer the whole world: and we thinke that the ſunne tunneth his courſe, and that the heauens ſtand ſtill: no it is the heauens that mooue his courſe, and the Sunne abideth perpetually in his place, he is permanent and fixed in his place, and although we ſée him beginning to aſcend in the Orient or Eaſt, at the higeſt in the Meridian or South, ſetting in the occident or Weſt, yet is he at the loweſt in Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentrion or North, and yet he mooueth not. It is the axle of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens that mooueth the whole firmrment, being a Chaos or confuſed thing, and for that proofe, I will ſhew thée this example: like as thou ſéeſt a bubble made of water and ſope blowne forth of a quill, is in forme of a confuſed maſſe or Chaos, and being in this forme, is moued at pleaſure of the winde which runneth round about that Chaos and mooueth him alſo round: euen ſo is the whole firmament or Chaos wherein are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſun, and the reſt of the planets turned and carryed at the pleaſure of the ſpirit of God, which is winde: Yea Chriſtian Reader, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and for the profite of thy ſoule, I will open vnto thée the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine opinion, touching the rule of this confuſed Chaos, farre more then my rude Germane Author, being poſſeſſed with the deuill, was able
<pb facs="tcp:15414:18"/>to vtter, and to proue ſome of my ſentences before to be true, looke into <hi>Geneſis,</hi> vnto the works of God, at the creation of the world, there ſhalt thou finde, that the ſpirit of God mooued vpon the waters, before hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth were made. Mark how he made it, and how by his word euery element tooke his place: theſe were not his works but is wordes, for all the words he vſed before, he concluded afterwards in one worke, which was in making man: marke reader with patience, for thy ſoules health, ſée into all that was done by the worde and worke of God: light and darknes was, the firmament ſtood, and there great ☿ and little light <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in it: the moſt waters were in one place, the earth was drye, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry element brought forth according to the word of God: now foloweth his workes, he made man after his owne Image, how, out of the earth? The earth will ſhape no Image without water: there was one of the elements. But all this while where was winde? All elements were at the worde of God: Man was made, &amp; in a forme by the worke of God, yet mooued not that worke, before God breathed the ſpirit of life into his noſthrils, &amp; made him a liuing ſoule: Here was the firſt winde and ſpirit of God, out of his own mouth, which we haue likewiſe from the ſame ſéede, which was only planted by God in <hi>Adam,</hi> which wind, breth or ſpirit, when he had receiued, he was liuing and mouing on earth, for it was ordayned of God for his habitation, but ſhe heauens are the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of the Lord: and like as I ſhewed before of the hubble, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed (Chaos made of water and ſope) through the wind &amp; breath of man is turned round, and caryed with euery winde, euen ſo the Firmament wherein the Sunne and the reſt of the planets are fixed, moued, turned, and caried, with the winde, breath, and ſpirit of God: for the heauens and firmaments are mooueable as the Chaos, but the Sunne is fixed in the firmament. And further (my good School-fellow) I was thus nigh the heauens, where me thought euery planet was but as half the earth, and vnder the firmament ruled the ſpirits in the aire, &amp; as I came down I looked vpon the world and the heauens, and me thought that the earth was incloſed (in compariſon) within the firmament, as the yolke of an Egge within the white &amp; me thought that the whole length of the earth was not a ſpan long: and the water was as if it had bin twice as broad and as long as the earth: euen thus at the eight daies end came I home againe, and fell aſléepe, and ſo I continued ſléeping, thrée dayes &amp; thrée nightes together: and the firſt houre I awaked, I fell freſh againe to my Kalender, and haue made them in right ample maner as you know, and to ſatiſfie your requeſt, for that you writ vnto me, I haue (in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of our olde friendſhip had at the vniuerſitie of <hi>Wittenberge</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:15414:19"/>declared vnto you my heauenly voyage, wiſhing no worſe vnto you then vnto my ſelfe, that is, that your minde were as mine in all reſpectes. <hi>Dixi. Doctor Fauſtus the Aſtrologian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus made his iourney through the principall and moſt famous lands in the world.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fau.</hi> hauing ouer-run fiftéene yeares of his appointed time, he tooke vpon him a iourney, with full pretence to ſée the whole world, and calling his Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> vnto him he ſaid: Thou knoweſt that thou art bound to me vpon conditions, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and fulfill my deſire in all thinges, wherefore my pretence is to viſite the whole face of the earth viſible and inuiſible when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me, therefore I enioyne and commaund thée to the ſame. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> anſwered, I am ready my Lord at thy command, and forthwith the ſpirit changed himſelfe into the likeneſſe of a flying horſe, ſaying, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſit vp, I am ready. Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> loftily fate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and forwards they went: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> came through many a Land and Prouince, as <hi>Pauonia, Auſtria, Germania, Bohemia, Sleſia, Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Miſſene, During, Franckland, Shawblandt, Byerlandt, Styria, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia, Poland, Litaw, Lieſland, Pruſſia, Denmarke, Muſcouia, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria, Turkie, Perſia, Cathai, Alexandria, Barbaria, Ginney, Peru,</hi> the ſtraightes <hi>Magenelanes, India,</hi> all about the frozen Zone, and <hi>Terra Incognita, Nona Hiſpaniola,</hi> the Iles of <hi>Terzera, Mederi, Saint Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els,</hi> the <hi>Canaries,</hi> and the <hi>Tenorifocie,</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>maine land, Portugall, Italie, Campania,</hi> the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> the Iles of <hi>Sicilia, Malta maioris, minoria,</hi> to the Knightes of the <hi>Rhodes, Candie,</hi> or <hi>Creet, Ciprus, Corinthe, Switzerland, France, Freeſland, Weſtpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, Zeland, Holland, Brabant,</hi> and all the <hi>17</hi> prouinces in <hi>Netherland, England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> all <hi>America</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſland,</hi> the out Iles of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the <hi>Orchades, Norway,</hi> the Biſhopricke of <hi>Breame,</hi> and ſo home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: all theſe kingdoms prouinces &amp; countries he paſſed in <hi>25</hi> daies, in which time he ſaw very little that delighted his mind: wherefore he took little reſt at home, &amp; burning in deſire to ſée more at large, &amp; to behold the ſecretes of each Kingdome, he ſet forwards againe on his iourney vpon his ſwift horſe <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> &amp; came to <hi>Trent,</hi> for that he chiefly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſée this towne and the monuments thereof: but there he ſaw not many wouders, except one faire pallace that belonged vnto the Biſhop, and alſo a mighty large caſtle that was built of brick, with <hi>3</hi> walls, &amp; <hi>3</hi> great trenches, ſo ſtrong that it was impoſſible for any princes power to win it: then he ſaw a Church wherin was buried <hi>Simeon,</hi> &amp; the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Popo:</hi> their tombes are of moſt ſumptuous Marble ſtone, cloſed
<pb facs="tcp:15414:19"/>and ioyned together with great bars of yron: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence he departed to <hi>Paris</hi> where he liked well the Academie: and what place or kingdom ſoeuer fel to his mind, the ſame he viſited. He came from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Mentz</hi> where the riuer of <hi>Maine</hi> fals into the <hi>Rhine,</hi> notwithſtanding he taried not long there but went into <hi>Campania</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>Neapolis</hi> in which he ſaw an innumerable ſort of Cloiſters. Nunries, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, great &amp; high houſes of ſtone, the ſtréets faire &amp; large, and ſtraight foorth from one end of the towne to the other as a line, and all the paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citty was of bricke, and the more it rayned in the towne the fairer the ſtréetes were: there ſaw he the tombe of <hi>Virgill,</hi> and the high way that he cut through the mighty hill of ſtone in one night, the whole length of an Engliſh mile: when he ſaw the number of Gallies &amp; Argo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zis that lay there at the citty head, the wind-mill that ſtood in the water, the caſtle in the water, and the houſes aboue the water, where vnder gallies might ride moſt ſafely from raine or wind: then he ſaw the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle on the hill euer the towne, and many monuments therein, alſo that hill called <hi>Veſuuius,</hi> wheron groweth all the Gréekiſh wine, &amp; moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſwéet Oliues. From thence he came to <hi>Venice,</hi> whereas he won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered not a little, to ſée a Citty ſo famouſly built ſtanding in the Sea, where through euery ſtréete the water came into ſuch largeneſſe, that great ſhips and barkes might paſſe from one ſtréete to another, hauing yet a way on both ſides the water whereon men and horſe might paſſe: He maruailed alſo how it was poſſible ſo much virtuall to be found in the towne, and ſo good cheape, conſidering that for a whole league, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing grew néere the ſame. He wondred not a little at the faireneſſe of S. <hi>Matkes</hi> place, and the ſumptuous Church ſtanding thereon, called S. <hi>Marke,</hi> how all the pauement was ſet with coloured ſtones, and all the Roode or loft of the Church double gilded ouer. Leauing this, he came to <hi>Padua</hi> beholding their manner of their Academie, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the mother or nurſe of Chriſtendome, there he heard the Doctors, and ſawe the moſt monuments in the Towne, entred his name in the Vniuerſitie of the Germane Nation, and wrote himſelfe Doctor <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> the vnſatiable ſpeculator: then ſaw he the worthieſe monument in the world for a Church, named S. <hi>Anthonies</hi> cloiſter, which for the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles thereof, and the contriuement of the Church, hath not the like in Chriſtendome. This towne is fenced about with thrée mighty walles of ſtone and earth, betwixt the which runneth goodly ditches of water: twice euery <hi>24.</hi> houres paſſeth boates betwixt <hi>Padua</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> with paſſengers, as they doe here betwixt <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Graueſend,</hi> and euen ſo farre they differ in diſtance: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> beheld likewiſe the counſaile-houſe
<pb facs="tcp:15414:20"/>and the Caſtle with no ſmall wonder. Well, forward he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> which lay, and doth yet lye on the Riuer <hi>Tibris,</hi> the which deuideth the City into two parts: ouer the Riuer are foure great ſtone Bridges, and vpon the one Bridge called <hi>Ponte S. Angelo,</hi> is the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> wherein are ſo many great, caſt Péeces as there are dayes in the yeare, and ſuch Péeces as will ſhoote ſeauen bullets off with one fire &amp; to this Caſtle commeth a pring vault from the Church and Pallace of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> through the which the Pope, (if any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be) paſſeth from his Pallace to the Caſtle for ſafegard: the Citty hath eleuen Gates, and a hill called <hi>Vaticinium,</hi> whereon St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church is built: In that Church the holy Fathers will heare no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, without the penitent bring money in his hand. Adioyning to this Church, is the <hi>Campo Santo</hi> the which <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> built: where euery day thirtéene Pilgrimes haue their dinners ſerued of the beſt: that is to ſay, Chriſt and his twelue Apoſtles. Hard by this he viſited the Churchyard of S. <hi>Peters,</hi> where he ſaw the Pyramides that <hi>Iulius Ceſar</hi> brought forth of <hi>Africa:</hi> it ſtood in <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his time leaning againſt the Church wall of Saint <hi>Peters,</hi> but now Pope <hi>Sextus</hi> hath erected it in the middle of S. <hi>Peters</hi> Churchyard, it is <hi>24.</hi> fatham long, and at the lower end ſixe fatham foure ſquare, and ſo foorth ſmaller vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: on the top is a Crucifixe of beaten Gold, the ſtone ſtandeth on foure Lyons of braſſe. Then he viſited the <hi>7.</hi> Churches of <hi>Rome</hi> that were St. <hi>Peters,</hi> S. <hi>Paules,</hi> S. <hi>Sebaſtians,</hi> S. <hi>Iohn Lateran,</hi> S. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> S. <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and S. <hi>Mary Maiora.</hi> Then went he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the towne, where he ſaw the Conduits of water that runne leuell through hill and dale, bringing water into the Towne fifteene Italian wiles off: other Monuments he ſaw too many to recits, but amongſt the reſt he was deſirous to ſée the Popes Court, and his manner of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice at his Table, wherfore he and his ſpirit made themſelues inuiſible and came to the Popes Court, and priuy chamber, where he was: there ſaw he many ſeruants attending on his holines, with many a flattering Sycophant carying of his meate, and there he marked the Pope and the manner of his ſeruice, which he ſeeing to be ſo vnmeaſurable and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous: Fie (quoth <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) why had not the diuell made a Pope of me? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſawe there notwithſtanding, ſuch as were like to himſelfe, proude, ſtoute, wilfull, gluttons, drunkards, whoremongers, breakers of wedlocke, and followers of all manner of vngodly exerciſes: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaid to his ſpirit, I thought that I had béene alone a hog or pork of the Diuels, but he muſt beare with me yet a little longer, for theſe hogs of <hi>Rome</hi> are already fatted, and fitted to make his roſt meate, the
<pb facs="tcp:15414:20"/>diuell might do well now to ſpit them all, and haue them to the fire, and let him ſummon the Nuns to turne the ſpits: for as none muſt confeſſe the Nun but the Fryer, ſo none ſhould turne the roſting Fryer but the Nun. Thus continued <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thrée dayes in the Popes Pallace and yet had no luſt to his meat, but ſtood ſtill in the Popes chamber and ſaw euery thing whatſoeuer it was: on a time the Pope would haue a feaſt prepared for the Cardinall of <hi>Pauia,</hi> and for his firſt welcome the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall was bidden to dinner: and as he ſate at meate, the Pope would euer be bleſſing and croſſing ouer his mouth, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> could ſuffer it no longer, but vp with his fiſt and ſmote the Pope on his face, and withall he laughed that the whole houſe might heare him, yet none of them ſaw him nor knew where he was: the Pope perſwaded his company that it was a damned ſoule, commanding Maſſe preſently to be ſaid for his deliuery out of Purgatory, which was done: the Pope ſate ſtil at meat, but when the latter meſſe came in to the Popes boord D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> laide hands thereon ſaying, this is mine, and ſo he tooke both diſh and meate and flew vnto the Capitoll or Campadolia, calling his ſpirit vnto him, and ſaid, come let vs be merry for thou muſt fetch me ſome wine and the cup that the Pope drinkes of, and here vpon <hi>monte caual,</hi> we will make good chéere in ſpight of the Pope and all his fat Abby-lubbers. His ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hearing this, departed towards the Popes chamber, where he found them yet ſitting and quaffing: wherefore he tooke from before the Pope the faireſt péece of plate or drinking goblet, and a flaggon of wine, and brought it to <hi>Fauſtus:</hi> but when the Pope and the reſt of his crue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued they were robbed, and knew not after what ſort, they perſwaded themſelues that it was that damned ſoule that before had vexed the Pope ſo, and that ſmot him on the face, wherfore he ſent commandment through the whole Citty of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they ſhould ſay Maſſe in euery Church, and ring all the bels for to lay the walking ſpirit, and to curſe him with bel, booke, and candle, that ſo inuiſibly had miſuſed the Popes holines, with the Cardinall of <hi>Pauia,</hi> and the reſt of their company: but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> notwithſtanding made good chéere with that which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled the Pope of, and in the middeſt of the order of S. <hi>Barnards</hi> bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed Fryers, as they were going on proceſſion through the market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place called <hi>campa de fiore,</hi> he let fal his plate, diſhes and cup: and with all for a farwell, he made ſuch a thunder-clap and ſtorme of raine, as though Heauen and earth ſhould haue met together, and ſo left <hi>Rome</hi> and came to <hi>Millaine</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> néere the Alpes or borders of <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where he praiſed much to his ſpirit the pleaſures of the place, the citty being founded in ſo braue a plaine, by the which ran moſt pleaſant
<pb facs="tcp:15414:21"/>riuers on euery ſide of the ſame, hauing beſides within the compaſſe or circuit of ſeauen miles, ſeauen ſmall Seas: He ſaw alſo therein many faire Pallaces and goodly buildings, the Dukes pallace, and the mighty ſtrong Caſtle which is in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r halfe the bignes of the towne: Moreouer, it liked him well to ſée the Hoſpitall of Saint <hi>Maries</hi> with diuers other thinges. He did there nothing worthy of memory, but he departed backe againe towards <hi>Bolognia,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Florence</hi> where he was well pleaſed to ſée the pleaſant walke of Marchants, the goodly vaults of the Citty, for that almoſt the whole Citty is vaulted, and the houſes themſelues are built outwardly, in ſuch ſort, that the people goe vnder them as vnder a vault: Then he peruſed the ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Church in the Dukes caſtle, called <hi>Noſtra Dama,</hi> our Ladyes Church, in which he ſaw many Monuments, as a marble doore, moſt huge to looke vpon: the gates of the caſtle are Bel-mottel, wherein are grauen the holy Patriarkes, with Chriſt and his twelue Apoſtles, and diuers other Hiſtories, out of the olde and new Teſtament. Then went he to <hi>Sena,</hi> where he highly praiſed the Church and Hoſpitall of <hi>Santa Maria Formoſa,</hi> with the goodly buildings, and eſpecially the fairenes and greatnes of the Citty &amp; beautifull women. Then came he to <hi>Lions</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where he marked the ſcituation of the Citty, which lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene two hills, inuironed with <hi>2.</hi> waters: one worthy Monument in the Citty pleaſed him well, that was the great Church with the Image therein: he commended the Cittie highly for the great reſort that it had vnto it of ſtrangers. From thence he went to <hi>Cullin,</hi> which lyeth vpon the riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> wherein he ſaw one of the auncienteſt Monuments of the world, the which was the Tombe of thrée Kinges, that came by the Angell of God, and their knowledge they had in the ſtarre, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Chriſt: which when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaw he ſpake in this manner, Ah alas good men how haue you erred, and loſt your way? you ſhould haue gone to <hi>Paleſtina</hi> and <hi>Bethlem</hi> in <hi>Iudea,</hi> how came you hither? Or belike after your death you were throwne into <hi>Mare Medeterraneum,</hi> about <hi>Tripolis</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and ſo you fléeted out of the ſtraigts of <hi>Gibalterra,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ocean ſea, and ſo into the bar of <hi>Portugall,</hi> and not finding any reſt you were driuen alongſt the coaſt of <hi>Gallicia, Biskay</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and into the narrow Seas, then from thence vnto <hi>Mare Germanicum,</hi> and ſo taken vp I thinke about the towne of <hi>Dort</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> you were brought to <hi>Cullin</hi> to be buried, or elſe I thinke you came more eaſily with a whirl-winde ouer the Alpes, and being thrown into the riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> it conuayed you to this place, where you are kept a Monument. There ſaw he the Church of S. <hi>Vrſula,</hi> where remaines a Monument
<pb facs="tcp:15414:21"/>of the <hi>1000.</hi> Virgins: it pleaſed him alſo to ſée the beauty of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Not farre from <hi>Cullin</hi> lyeth the towne of <hi>Ach,</hi> where he ſaw the gorgeous temple that the Emperour <hi>Carolus quartus</hi> built of Marble ſtone for a remembrance of him, to the end that all his ſucceſſors ſhould there be crowned. From <hi>Cullin</hi> &amp; <hi>Ach</hi> he went to <hi>Geneua,</hi> a city in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy,</hi> lying néere <hi>Switzerland,</hi> it is a towne of great traffike, the Lord thereof is a Biſhop, whoſe wine ſeller <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and his ſpirit viſited, for the loue of his good wine. From thence he went to <hi>Strasburg,</hi> where he beheld the faireſt temple that euer he had ſéene in his life before, for on euery ſide thereat he might ſée through it, euen from the couering of the Minſter to the top of the Pinicle, and it is named one of the wonders of the world: wherefore he demanded why it was called <hi>Strasburg?</hi> his ſpirit anſwered, becauſe it hath ſo many high wayes comming to it on euery ſide, for <hi>Stros</hi> in Dutch is a high way, and hereof came the name: yea (ſaid <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi>) the Church which thou ſo wondereſt at, hath more reuenues belonging to it then the twelue Duks of <hi>Sleſia</hi> are worth, for there pertaine vnto this Church fifty ſiue townes, and foure hundreth ſixtie thrée Villages, beſides many houſes in the Towne. From thence went <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to <hi>Baſil</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where the riuer of <hi>Rhine</hi> runneth through the Towne, parting the ſame as the Riuer of <hi>Thames</hi> doth <hi>London:</hi> in this towne of <hi>Baſil</hi> he ſaw many rich monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the towne walled with bricke, and round about it without it goeth a great trench: no Church pleaſed him but the Ieſuites Church, which was ſumptuouſly builded, and ſet full of Alablaſter Pillars: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> demanded of his Spirit how it tooke the name of <hi>Baſil?</hi> his Spirit made anſwere and ſaid, that before this cittie was found, there vſed a <hi>Bafiliſcus</hi> a kinde of Serpent, this Serpent killed as many men, women, and children as he tooke a fight of, but there was a Knight that made himſelfe a couer of chriſtall to come ouer his head and ſo downe to the ground, and being firſt couered with a blacke cloath, ouer that he put the chriſtall, and ſo boldly went to ſée the <hi>Baſiliſcus,</hi> and finding the place where ſhe haunted, he expecting her comming, euen before the mouth of her caue, where ſtanding a while, the <hi>Baſiliſcus</hi> came foorth, who when ſhe ſawe her owne venomous ſhadow in the Chriſtall, ſhe ſplit in a thouſand péeces: wherefore the Knight was richly rewarded of the Emperour: after the which the Knight founded this towne vpon the place where he had flaine the Serpent, and gaue it the name of <hi>Baſil,</hi> in remembrance of his déed.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Baſil Fauſtus</hi> went to <hi>Coſtuitz</hi> in <hi>Sweitz</hi> at the head of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> where is a moſt ſumptuous bridge that goeth ouer the <hi>Rhine,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15414:22"/>euen from the gates of the towne, vnto the other ſide of the ſtreame: at the head of the riuer of <hi>Rhine,</hi> is a ſmall Sea, called of the <hi>Switzers</hi> the blacke ſea, twenty thouſand paces long, and fifty hundred paces broad. The towne <hi>Coſtuitz</hi> tooke the name of this: the Emperour gaue it to a Clowne, for expounding of his Riddle, wherfore the Clowne named the towne <hi>Coſtuitz,</hi> that is in Engliſh, coſt nothing. From <hi>Coſtuitz</hi> he came to <hi>Vim,</hi> where he ſawe the ſumptuous Town-houſe, built by two and fifty of the auncient Senators of the Citye, It tooke the name of <hi>Vlm,</hi> for that the whole land there about, are full of Elmes: but <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> minding to departe from thence, his ſpirit ſaid vnto him, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thinke of the Towne as thou wilt, it hath three Dukdomes belonging to it, the which they haue bought with ready money. From <hi>Vlm</hi> he came vnto <hi>Wartzburg,</hi> the chiefeſt Towne in <hi>Frankeland,</hi> wherein the Biſhop altogether kéepeth his Court, through the which Towne paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the riuer of <hi>Mayne,</hi> that runs into the <hi>Rhine:</hi> there about groweth ſtrong and pleaſant wine, the which <hi>Fauſtus</hi> well prooued: The Caſtle ſtandeth on a hill, on the north ſide of the Towne, at the foote whereof runneth the riuer: this towne is ful of beggerly Fryers, Nuns, prieſts and Ieſuites: for there are fiue ſortes of begging Fryers, beſides thrée Cloyſters of Nunnes: At the foot of the Caſtle ſtands a Church, in the which there is an Alter, where are engrauen all the foure Elements and all the orders and degrées in heauen, that any man of vnderſtanding whoſoeuer that hath a ſight thereof, may ſay, that it is the Artificialleſt thing that euer he behold. From thence he went to <hi>Norenberg,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he went by the way, his ſpirit informed him, that the town was named of <hi>Claudius Tiberius,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nero</hi> the tyrant. In the towne are two famous Cathedral Churches, the one called <hi>S. Sabolt,</hi> th'other Saint <hi>Laurence:</hi> in which Church ſtandeth all the Reliques of <hi>Carolus magnus,</hi> that is to ſay, his Cloake, his hoſe and doblet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Sword and Crowne, his Scepter and his Apple: It hath a very glorious guilden Conduit in the Market place of <hi>S. Laurence:</hi> in which Conduit is the ſpear that thruſt our Sauiour into the ſide, &amp; a péece of the holy Croſſe: the wall is called, <hi>The faire wall of Norenberg,</hi> and hath <hi>528</hi> ſtréetes, <hi>160.</hi> welles, foure great &amp; two ſmall Clockes, ſix great Gates, &amp; two ſmal doores, eleuen ſtone Bridges, twelue ſmall hills, ten faire market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places, thirtéen common Hot-houſes, ten Churches: within the towne are thirty whéeles of water-milles: it hath <hi>132</hi> tall Ships, two migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Towne walles of hewen Stone and earth, with very déep trenches: the wals haue <hi>180</hi> Towres about them, and foure faire platforms, ten Apothecaries, ten Doctors of the Common Lawe, fourtéene Doctors
<pb facs="tcp:15414:22"/>of Phiſicke. From <hi>Norenburg,</hi> he went to <hi>Auſpurg</hi> where, at the breake of the day, he demanded of his ſpirit, whereupon the towne tooke his name: this towne (quoth he) hath had many names, when it was firſt built, it was called <hi>Vindelica:</hi> ſecondly it was called <hi>Zizaria,</hi> the yron bridge: laſtly, by the Emperour <hi>Octauius Auguſtus</hi> it was called <hi>Auguſta,</hi> and by the corruption of language, the Germans haue named it Auſpurg. Now for becauſe that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had béene there before, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted without viſiting their monuments to <hi>Rauenſpurg,</hi> where his ſpirit certified him that the Citty had ſeauen names: the firſt <hi>Tyberia,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Quadratis,</hi> the third <hi>Heaſpalis,</hi> the fourth <hi>Regionopolis,</hi> the fift <hi>Imbripolis,</hi> the ſixt <hi>Ratisbona,</hi> the laſt <hi>Rauenſpurg.</hi> The ſcituation of this Citty pleaſed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> well, alſo the ſtrong and ſumptuous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: by the walles thereof runneth the riuer <hi>Danubia,</hi> in Dutch called <hi>Donow,</hi> into the which not farre from the compaſſe of the Citty, falleth neere hand thréeſcore other ſmall riuers &amp; freſh waters: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> alſo liked the ſumptuous ſtone Bridge ouer the ſame water, with the Church ſtanding thereon, the which was founded <hi>An. 1115.</hi> the name whereof is called S. <hi>Remadian:</hi> in this towne <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went into the Celler of an Inholder, and let out all the wine and béere that was in the celler. After the which feate he returned into <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Bauaria</hi> a right princely towne, the Towne appeared as if it were new, with great ſtréets therein both of breadth and length from <hi>Mentz</hi> to <hi>Saitburg,</hi> where the Biſhop is alwaies reſident: here ſaw he all the commodities that were poſſible to be ſéene, for at the hill he ſawe the forme of a bell made in Chriſtall, an huge thing to looke vpon, that euery yeare grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth bigger and bigger, by reaſon of the fréezing colde. From thence he went to <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> this Towne is of ſo great antiquitie, that it is not poſſible to finde the like. In this towne (ſaid the ſpirit) is more wine then water, for all vnder the towne are wels, the which are filled euery yeare with wine, and all the water that they haue, runneth by the Towne, that is, the riuer <hi>Danubia.</hi> From thence he went into <hi>Prage,</hi> the chiefe Citty in <hi>Bohemia:</hi> this is deuided into thrée partes, that is, old <hi>Prage,</hi> new <hi>Prage,</hi> and little <hi>Prage.</hi> Little <hi>Prage</hi> is the place where the Emperors court is placed, vpon an excéeding high mountaine, there is a Caſtle where are two faire Churches, in the one he found a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which might well haue béene a mirror for himſelfe, and that was the Sepulcher of a notable Coniurer, which by his magicke had ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted his Sepulcher, that whoſouer ſet foote thereon, ſhould be ſure neuer to dye in their beds. From this Caſtle he came downe and went euer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bridge. This bridge hath twenty &amp; foure Arches. In the middle
<pb facs="tcp:15414:23"/>of the bridge ſtands a very faire Monument, being a croſſe builded of ſtone, and moſt artificially carued. From thence he came into the olde <hi>Prage,</hi> the which is ſeperated from the new <hi>Prage,</hi> with an excéeding déepe ditch, and round about incloſed with a well of bricke. Vnto this is adioyning the Iewes Towne, wherein are thirteene thouſand men, women and children, all Iewes. There he viewed the Colledge and the Garden where all manner of ſauage beaſts are kept, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce he ſet a compas round about the thrée townes, whereat he wondred great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſée ſo mighty a Citty ſtand all within the walls. From <hi>Prage</hi> he flew in the ayre and bethought himſelfe what he might doe, or which way to take, ſo he looked round about, &amp; behold be eſpied a paſſing faire Citty which lay not farre from <hi>Prage,</hi> about ſome foure and twenty miles, and that was <hi>Breſſaw</hi> in <hi>Sclefia,</hi> in the which when he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, it ſéemed to him that he had béene in Paradiſe, ſo neate and cleane was the ſtréets, and ſo ſumptuous was their buildings. In the Citty he ſaw not many wonders, except the braſen Virgin that ſtandeth on a bridge ouer the water, and vnder the which ſtandeth a mill like a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mill, which virgin is made to doe execution vpon thoſe diſobedient towne borne children that be ſo wilde that their parents cannot bridle them: which when any ſuch are found with ſome haynous offence tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſhame of their parents &amp; kindred, they are brought to kiſſe this virgin, which openeth her arme, the perſon then to be executed kiſſeth her, then doth ſhe cloſe her armes together with ſuch violence, that ſhe cruſheth out the breath of the partie, breaketh his bulke &amp; ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but being dead, ſhe openeth her armes againe and letteth the party fall into the mill, where he is ſtamped in ſmall morſels, which the water carryeth away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that no part of him is found againe. From <hi>Breſſaw</hi> he went toward <hi>Cracona,</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>Polonia,</hi> where he beheld the Acadamie the which pleaſed him wonderfull will. In this Citty the King moſt commonly holdeth his Court at a caſtle, in which Caſtle are many famous Monuments. There is a moſt ſumptuous Church in the ſame, in which ſtandeth a ſiluer Altar gilded, &amp; ſet with rich ſtones, and ouer it is a conueyance ful of all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of ſiluer ornaments belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Maſſe. In the church hangeth the iawbones of a huge dragon that kept the rocke before the Caſtle was edified thereon. It is full of all manner of munition, and hath alwaies virtual for <hi>3.</hi> yeares to ſerue <hi>2.</hi> thouſand men. Through the towne runneth a riuer called the <hi>Veſtual</hi> or <hi>Wiſſell,</hi> where ouer is a faire woodden bridge. This water d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uideth the towne and <hi>Caſmere,</hi> in this <hi>Caſmere</hi> dwelleth the Iewes being a ſmall walled Towne by themſelues, to the number of <hi>25000.</hi> men,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:23"/>women and children: within one mile of the towne there is a ſalt mine where they finde ſiones of pure ſalt of <hi>1000.</hi> pound, <hi>2000.</hi> pound, or more in weight, and that in great quantity. This ſalt is as blacke as the <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> coales when it comes out of the mines, but being beaten to powder it is as white as ſnowe. The like they haue foure mile from thence at a towne called <hi>Buchma.</hi> From thence <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went to <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>z,</hi> the captaine therof was called <hi>Deu Spiket Iordan:</hi> in this towne are many monuments, as the tombe or ſepulcher of Chriſt, in as ample maner as that is at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> at the proper coſts of a Gentleman that went thriſe to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> from that place and returned againe. Not far from that towne is a new towne, wherein is a Nunry of the order of S. <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> into which order may none come except they be Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, and well formed, and faire to looke vpon, the which pleaſed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> well, but hauing a will to trauaile further, and to ſée more wonders, mounting vp towards the eaſt, ouer many lands and prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as into <hi>Hungaria, Tranſiluania, Shede, Ingatz, Sardenia,</hi> and ſo into <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where the Turkiſh Emperor kept his court: this citty was ſurnamed by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the founder thereof, being builded of very faire ſtone. In the ſame the great Turke hath thrée faire pallaces, the walls are ſtrong, the pinacles are very huge, and the ſtreets large, but this liked not <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that one man might haue ſo many wiues as he would: the ſea runneth hard by the Citie, the wall hath <hi>11.</hi> gates: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> abode th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re a certaine time to ſée the manner of the Turkiſh Emperours ſeruice at his table, where he ſaw his royall ſeruice to be ſuch, that he thought if all the Chriſtian Princes ſhould banquet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and euery one adorne the feaſt to the vttermoſt, they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to compare with the Turke for his table, and the reſt of his country ſeruice: wherefore it ſo ſpighted <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> that he vowed to be reuenged on him, for his pomp he thought was more fit for himſelfe, wherefore as the turke ſat at meate <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhewed him a little apiſh play: for round about the priuy chamber he ſent forth flaſhing flames of fire, inſomuch that the whole company forſooke their meate and fled, except onely the great Turke himſelfe, him <hi>Fauſtus</hi> charmed in ſuch ſort, that he could neither riſe nor fall, neither could any man pull him vp: With this was the hall ſo light, as if the Sunne had ſhined in the houſe, then came <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in forme of a Pope to the great Turke, ſaying, all haile Emperour, now art thou honoured that I ſo worthily appeare vnto thée as thy <hi>Mahomet</hi> was wont to doe, hereupon he vaniſhed, &amp; forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it thundred, that the whole Pallace ſhooke: the Turke greatly meruailed what this ſhould be that ſo vexed him, and was perſwaded
<pb facs="tcp:15414:24"/>by his chiefeſt counſellors that it was <hi>Mahomet</hi> his Prophet which had ſo appeared vnto them, whereupon the Turke commanded them to fall downe on their knées, and to giue him thankes for doing them ſo great honour as to ſhew himſelfe vnto them: but the next day <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went into the Caſtle where he kept his Wiues and Concubines, in the which Caſtle might no man vpon the paine of death come, except thoſe that were appointed by the great Turke to doe them ſeruice, and they were all gelded: which when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> perceiued, he ſaid to his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> how likeſt thou this ſport? are not theſe faire ladies greatly to be pittied that thus conſume their youth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of one only man? Why (quoth the ſpirit) maiſt not thou in ſtead of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour embrace his faire ladies? doe what thy heart deſireth heerein, and I will aid thée, and what thou wiſheſt thou ſhalt haue it performed: wherefore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> (being before this counſaile apt enough to put ſuch matters in practiſe) cauſed a great fogge to be round about the Caſtle, both within and without, and he himſelfe appeared amongſt the Ladies in all points as they vſe to paint their <hi>Mahomet:</hi> at which ſight the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies fell on their knées and worſhipped him. Then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke the faireſt by the hand and led her into a chamber, where after his maner he fell to dalliance, and thus he continued a whole day and a night: and when he had delighted himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe ſufficiently with her he put her away. and made his ſpirit bring him another, ſo likewiſe he kept with her <hi>24.</hi> houres play, cauſing his ſpirit to fetch him moſt dainty fare, and ſo he paſſed away ſixe dayes, hauing each day his pleaſure of a ſundry Ladie, and that of the faireſt: all which time the fog was ſo thicke and ſo ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that they within the houſe thought they had béene in hell for the time and they without wondred thereat, in ſuch ſort that they went to their prayers, calling on their God <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and worſhiping of his Image. Wherfore the ſixt day <hi>Fauſtus</hi> exalted himſelfe into the aire like to a Pope, in ſight of the great Turke and his people. And he had no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner departed the Caſtle but the fog vaniſhed away: whence preſently the Turke ſent for his Wiues and Concubines, demaunding of them if they knew the cauſe why the Caſtle was beſet with a miſt ſo long? They ſaid that it was the God <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelfe that cauſed it, and how he was in the Caſtle perſonally full ſixe dayes: and for more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty he hath line with ſixe of vs ſixe nights one after another. The Turke hearing this, fell downe vpon his knées, and gaue <hi>Mahomet</hi> thankes, deſiring him to forgiue him for béeing offended with his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Caſtle &amp; wiues thoſe ſixe daies but the Turke commanded that thoſt whom <hi>Mahomet</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> line by ſhould be moſt carefully looked vnto,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:24"/>perſwading himſelfe (and ſo did all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole people that knew of it) that out of them <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſhould be raiſed a mighty generation, but firſt he demanded of the ſixe Ladies if <hi>Mahomet</hi> had not actuall copulation with them according as earthly men haue? yea my Lord (quoth one) as if you had béen there your ſelfe you could not haue mended it, for he lay with vs ſtarke naked, kiſſed and colled vs, and ſo delighted me, that for my part I would he came two or thrée times a weeke to ſerue me in ſuch ſort againe. From whence <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went to <hi>Alkar,</hi> the which before times was called <hi>Chairam</hi> or <hi>Memphis.</hi> In this Citty the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Souldan holdeth his court. From thence the riuer <hi>Nilus</hi> hath his firſt head and ſpring, it is the greateſt freſh water riuer that is in the whole world, and alwaies when the Sun is in <hi>Cancer</hi> it ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the whole land of Egypt: Then he returned againe towards the Northeaſt, and to the Towne of <hi>Ofen</hi> and <hi>Sebata</hi> in <hi>Hungaria.</hi> This <hi>Of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> is the chiefeſt Citty in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and ſtandeth in a fertile ſoyle, wherein groweth moſt excellent wine, and not farre from the Towne there is a Well called <hi>Zipzar,</hi> the water whereof changeth Iron into Copper: there are mines of gold and ſiluer, &amp; all manner of metall: we <hi>Germanes</hi> call this towne <hi>Ofen;</hi> but in the <hi>Hungarian</hi> ſpeach it is <hi>Start.</hi> In the towne ſtandeth a very faire Caſtle and very well fortified. From thence he went to <hi>Auſtria,</hi> &amp; through <hi>Sleſia</hi> into <hi>Saxony,</hi> vnto the towns of <hi>Magdeburg</hi> and <hi>Lipzig,</hi> and <hi>Lubeck, Magdeburg</hi> is a Biſhoprick: in this citty is one of the pittchers wherein Chriſt changed the water into wine at <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Gallile.</hi> At <hi>Lipzig</hi> nothing pleaſed <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſo well as the great veſſell in the Caſtle made of wood, the which is bound about with <hi>24</hi> yron hoopes, and euery hoope weigheth <hi>200</hi> pound weight: you muſt goe vpon a ladder <hi>30</hi> ſteppes high before you can looke into it: he ſaw alſo the new churchyard where it is walled, &amp; ſtandeth vpon a faire plaine, the yard is <hi>200</hi> paces long, and round about the ſide of the wall are goodly places ſeparated due from each other to ſée ſepulchers in, which in the middle of the yard ſtandeth very ſumptuous: therein ſtandeth a Pulpit of white worke and gold. From hence he came to <hi>Lubeck</hi> and <hi>Hamburg,</hi> where he made no abode, but away againe to <hi>Erford</hi> in <hi>Duringen,</hi> where he viſited the <hi>Freſcold,</hi> and from <hi>Erfold</hi> he went home to <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> when he had ſéen and viſited many a ſtrange place, being from home one yeare and a halfe, in which time he wrought more wonders then are here declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>How Fauſtus had a ſight of Paradiſe. Chap. 34.</head>
               <p>AFter this Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſet forth againe to viſite the countries of <hi>Spaine, Portugall, France, England, Scotland, Denmarke, Sweden
<pb facs="tcp:15414:25"/>Poland, Muſcouy, India, Cataia, Affrica, Perſia,</hi> and laſtly into <hi>Barbaria</hi> amongſt the <hi>Blackamoores.</hi> And in all his wandring he was deſirous to viſite the ancient monuments and mighty hills: amongſt the reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the high hill called the <hi>Treno Reife,</hi> was deſirous to reſt vpon it: from thence he went into the Ile of <hi>Britanny,</hi> wherein he was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delighted to ſée the faire water, and warme Bathes, the diuers ſorts of metal, with many precious ſtones, &amp; diuers other comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ities, the which <hi>Fauſtus</hi> brought thence with him: He was alſo at the <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hades</hi> behind <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he ſaw the trée that bringeth forth fruite, that when it is ripe openeth and falleth into the water, wherein engendreth a certaine kinde of fowle or bird, theſe Ilands are in number <hi>23.</hi> but ten of them are not habitable, the other thirtéene are inhabited. From hence he went to the Hill <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> which is the higheſt in all that <hi>Tropick,</hi> it lieth néere the borders of <hi>Scythia:</hi> hereon <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſtood and beheld many lands and Kingdomes, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being on ſuch an high hill, thought to looke ouer all the world, &amp; beyond, for he went to ſée Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, but he durſt not commune with his Spirit thereof: and being on the hill of <hi>Caucaſus</hi> he ſaw the whole land of <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Scytbia,</hi> and as he looked towards the Eaſt, he ſaw a mighty cleare ſtrike of fire com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from heauen vpon the earth, euen as it had béene one of the beams of the Sunne, he ſaw in the valley foure mighty waters ſpringing: one had his courſe towards <hi>India,</hi> the ſecond towards <hi>Egypt,</hi> the third and fourth towards <hi>Armenia.</hi> When he ſaw theſe, he would néeds know of his ſpirit what waters they were, and from whence they came: His ſpirit gaue him gently an anſwere, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is Paradiſe that lieth ſo farre in the Eaſt, the Garden that God himſelfe hath planted with all manner of pleaſure, and the fiery ſtreame that thou ſéeſt, is the walls or fence of the garden, but the cléere light thou ſéeſt ſo farre off, that is the Angell that hath the cuſtody therof with a fiery ſword, and although that thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe to be hard by, thou haſt yet further thether from hence then thou haſt euer béene: the water that thou ſéeſt diuided in foure parts is the water that iſſueth out of the well in the middle of Paradiſe. The firſt is called <hi>Ganges</hi> or <hi>Piſſon,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Gihon,</hi> the <hi>3. Tygris,</hi> and the <hi>4. Euphrates:</hi> alſo thou ſéeſt that he ſtandeth vnder <hi>Libra</hi> and <hi>Aries,</hi> right toward the <hi>Zenith,</hi> and vpon this fiery wall ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Angell <hi>Michaell</hi> with his flaming ſword to kéepe the frée of life, the which he hath in charge: but the ſpirit ſaid to <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> neither then nor I, nor any after vs, yea all men whoſoeuer are denied to viſit it, or to come any néerer then we be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:25"/>
               <head>Of a certaine Comet that appeared in Germany, and how Doctor Fauſtus was deſired by certaine friends of his to knowe the meaning thereof. Chap. 24.</head>
               <p>IN <hi>Germany,</hi> ouer the Towne of St. <hi>Eizleben</hi> was ſéene a mightie great Comet, whereat the people wondred: but Doctor <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was asked of certaine of his friends his iudgement or opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſhe matter? Whereupon he anſwered, it falleth out often by the courſe and change of the ſun and moone, that the ſun is vnder the earth, and the moone aboue: but when the moone draweth néere the change, then is the ſun ſo ſtrong, that it taketh away all the light of the moone, in ſuch ſort, that he is as red as blood, and the contrary, after they haue béene together, the moone taketh her light againe from him, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in light to the full, ſhe will be as red as the ſunne was before, and changeth her ſelfe into diuers and ſundry colours, of the which ſpringeth a prodigious Monſter or as you call it a Comet, which is a figure or token appointed of God as a forewarning of his diſpleaſure: as at one time, he ſendeth hunger, plague, ſword, or ſuch like: being all tokens of his iudgement: the which Comet commeth through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the ſunne and moone begetting a monſter, whoſe father is the Sunne, and whoſe mother is the Moone ☉ and ☾.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>A queſtion put forth to D. Fauſtus concerning the ſtarres. Chap. 25.</head>
               <p>THere was a learned man of the towne of <hi>Holberſtat,</hi> named <hi>N.W.</hi> who inuited D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to his table, but falling into communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before ſupper was ready, they looked out of the window, and ſéeing many ſtars in the firmament, this man being a Doctor of Phiſicke and a good Aſtrologian, ſaid, D <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I haue inuited you as my gueſt, hoping that you will take it in good part with me, and withall I requeſt you to impart vnto me ſome of your experience in the ſtars and planets. And ſéeing a ſtar fall, he ſaid, I pray you <hi>Fauſtus</hi> what is the condition, qualitie or greateſt of the ſtarres in the firmament? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered him: My friend and brother, you ſée that the ſtarres that fall from heauen, when they come to the earth they be very ſmall to our thinking as candels, but being fixed in the firmament, there are many as great as this Citty, ſome as great as a Prouince or Dukedome, other as great as the whole earth: other ſome far greater then the earth: as the length and the breadth of the heauen is greater then the earth twelue times, and from the height of the heauens there is ſcarſe and earth to be ſéene, yea the planets in the heauens are ſome ſo great as this land, ſome ſo great as the whole Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome as <hi>Turky,</hi> yea one ſo great as the whole world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:26"/>
               <head>How Fauſtus was asked a queſtion concerning the Spirits that vexe men. Chap. 26.</head>
               <p>THat is moſt true (ſaith he to <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) concerning the Starres and Planets: but I pray you, in what kinde or manner doe the ſpirits vſe to vex men ſo little by day, and ſo greatly by night? Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered, becauſe the Spirits are by God forbidden the light, their dwelling is in darknes, and the clearer the Sun ſhineth the further the ſpirits haue their abiding from it, but in the night when it is darke, they haue their familiarity and abiding néere vnto vs men. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the night we ſée not the Sun, yet the brightnes thereof ſo lightneth the firſt moouing of the firmament, as it doth héer on earth in the day, by which reaſon we are able to ſee the Stars and Planets in the night: euen ſo the raies of the Sun piercing vpwards into the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, the Spirits abandon the place and ſo come néere vs on earth, the darknes filling our heads with heauy dreames and fond fancies, with ſchrikng and crying in many deformed ſhapes: and ſome times when men goe foorth without light, there falleth to them a feare, that their haire ſtandeth on end: ſo many ſtart in their ſléepe, thinking there is a ſpirit by him, gropeth or féeleth for him, going round about the houſe in his ſléepe, and many ſuch like fancies: and all this is for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the night the ſpirits are more familiarly by vs, that we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of their company, and ſo they cary vs, blinding vs, and plaguing vs more then we are able to perceiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus was asked a queſtion cuncerning the Starres that fall from heauen. Chap. 27.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being demaunded the cauſe why the ſtars fell from heauen, he anſwered that it is but our opinion, for if one ſtar fall, it is the great iudgement of God vpon vs, as a forewarning of ſome great thing to come, for when we thinke that a ſtarre falleth, it is but a ſparke that iſſueth from a candle or a flame of fire, for if it were a ſubſtantiall thing, we ſhould not ſo ſoone looſe the ſight of them as we doe. And likewiſe if ſo be that we ſée as it were a ſtreame of fire fall from the firmament as it oft hapneth, yet are they no ſtarres, but as it were a flame of fire vaniſhing, but the ſtars are ſubſtantiall, therfore are they firme &amp; not falling: if there fall any, it is a ſigne of ſome great matter to come as a ſcourge to a people or country, and then ſuch ſtars falling, the gates of heauen are opened, and the clouds ſend foorth floods, or other plagues, to the dammage of the whole land and people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:26"/>
               <head>Fauſtus was asked a queſtion concerning thunder. Chap. 28.</head>
               <p>IN the month of Auguſt, there was ouer <hi>Wittenberg</hi> a mighty great lightning and thunder, and as Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was ieſting merily in the market place with certaine of his friends &amp; companions being Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, they deſired him to tell them the cauſe of that weather? <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered: It hath béen commonly ſéene heretofore, that before a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-clap, fell a ſhower of raine, or a gale of winde, for commonly after a winde followeth a raine, and after a raine a thunder-clap, ſuch things come to paſſe when the foure windes méet together in the heauens, the ayrie clouds are by force beaten againſt the fixed Chriſtall firmament, but when the ayrie clouds méet with the firmament, they are congealed, and ſo ſtrike and ruſh againſt the firmament, as great péeces of yee when they méet on the water, the each other ſoundeth in our eares, and that we call Thunder, which indéed is none other then you haue heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third and laſt of Doctor Fauſtus his merry conceits, ſhewing after what ſort he practiſed Nicromancie in the Courts of great Princes, and laſtly of his fearefull and pittifullend.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>How the Emperour Carolus Quintus requeſted of Fauſtus to ſee ſome of his cunning, wherunto he agreed. Chap. 29.</head>
               <p>THe Emperour <hi>Carolus</hi> the fift of that name was perſonally with the reſt of his Nobles and Gentlemen at the towne of <hi>Inſzburck,</hi> where he kept his Court, vnto the which alſo Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> reſorted, and being there well known of diuers Nobles &amp; gentlemen, he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited into the court to meat, euen in the preſence of the Emperor, whom when the Emperor ſaw, he looked earneſtly on him, thinking him by his lookes to be ſome wonderfull fellow: wherefore he asked one of his Nobles whom he ſhould be? he anſwered that he was called Doctor <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> Whereupon the Emperor held his peace vntill he had taken his repaſt: after which he called vnto him <hi>Fauſtus</hi> into his priuie cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: whither being come, he ſaid vnto him: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> I haue heard much of thée, that thou art excellent in the blacke Art, and none like thée in mine Empire, for men ſay that thou haſt a familiar ſpirit with thée, and that thou canſt do what thou liſt: it is therfore (ſaid the Emperor) my requeſt of thée, that thou let me ſée a proofe of thine experience, and I vow vnto thee by the honor of my Emperiall Crowne, none euill ſhall happen vnto thée for ſo doing. Hereupon Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered his Maieſtie, that vpon theſe conditions he was ready in any thing that he could, to doe his highnes commaundment in what ſeruice he would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him. Well, heare then what I ſay (quoth the Emperor.) Being
<pb facs="tcp:15414:27"/>once ſolitary in my houſe, I called to minde mine elders and anceſters, how it was poſſible for them to attaine vnto ſo great degrée of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, yea ſo high, that we the ſucceſſours of that line are neuer able to come neere. As for example, the great and mighty Monarch of the world <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> was ſuch a Lanterne and ſpectacle to all his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, as the chronicles makes mention of ſo great riches, conquering and ſubduing ſo many kingdomes, the which I and theſe that follow me (I feare) ſhall neuer be able to attaine vnto: wherefore <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> my hearty deſire is, that thou wouldeſt vouchſafe to let me ſee that <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> and his Paramour the which was praiſed to be ſo faire, and I pray thée ſhew mée them in ſuch ſort that I may ſée their perſonages, ſhape, geſture and apparell, as they vſed in their life time, and that héere before my face, to the end that I may ſay I have my long deſire fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and to praiſe thee to be a famous man in thine art and experience. D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered: My moſt excellent Lord, I am ready to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh your requeſt in all things, ſo farre foorth as I and my ſpirit are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to performe: yet your maieſty ſhal know, that their dead bodies are not able ſubſtantially to be brought before you, but ſuch ſpirits as haue ſéene <hi>Alexander</hi> and his Paramour aliue, ſhall appeare vnto you in maner and forme as they both liued in their moſt flouriſhing time: and herewith I hope to pleaſe your imperiall maieſty. Then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went a little aſide to ſpeake to his ſpirit, but he returned againe preſently, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: now if it pleaſe your maieſty you ſhall ſée them, yet vpon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you demand no queſtion of them, nor ſpeake vnto them, which the Emperour agréed vnto. Wherewith Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> opened the priuie chamber doore, where preſently entred the great and mighty Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Alexander Magnus,</hi> in all thinges to looke vpon as if he had bin gliue, in proportion a ſtrong thicke ſet man, of a middle ſtature, blacke haire, and that both thicke and curled, head and beard, red chéekes, and a broad face, with eyes like a <hi>Baſilicke,</hi> he had a compleat harnes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and grauen exceeding rich to looke vpon: and ſo paſſing towards the Emperour <hi>Carolus,</hi> he made lowe and reuerent curteſie: whereat the Emperour <hi>Carolus</hi> would haue ſtood vp to receiue and gréete him with the like reuerence: but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke holde of him, and would not permit him to doe it. Shortly after <hi>Alexander</hi> made humble reuerence and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt out again: and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the doore his paramour met him, ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in, made the Emperour likewiſe reuerence: ſhe was cloathed in blew veluer, wrought and imbroidered with Pearles and gold, ſhe was alſo excellent faire, like milke and bloud mixed, tall and ſlender, with a face round as an apple: and thus ſhe paſſed certain times vp and
<pb facs="tcp:15414:27"/>downe the houſe, which the Emperour marking, ſaid to himſelfe: now haue I ſéene two perſons which my heart hath long wiſhed to behold: and ſure it cannot otherwiſe be (ſaid he to himſelfe) but that the ſpirits haue changed themſelues into theſe formes, and haue not deceiued me, calling to minde the woman that raiſed the Prophet <hi>Samuell:</hi> and for that the Emperor would be the more ſatiſfied in the matter he ſaid I haue often heard that behinde her necke ſhe had a great wart or wen, wherfore he tooke <hi>Fauſtus</hi> by the hand without any words, and went to ſée if it were alſo to be ſéen on her or not: but ſhe perceiuing that he came to her, bowed downe her neck, where he ſaw a great wart, and hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe vaniſhed, leauing the Emperor and the reſt well contented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus in the ſight of the Emperour, coniured a paire of Harts hornes vpon a Knights head that ſlept out at a cazement. Chap. 30.</head>
               <p>VVHen Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had accompliſhed the Emperors deſire in all things as he was requeſted, he went foorth into a gallery, and leaning ouer a raile to looke into the priuy garden, he ſaw many of the Emperors courtiers walking and talking together, and caſting his eyes now this way, now that way, he eſpied a Knight leauing out at a window of the great hall, who was faſt a ſléepe (for in thoſe daies it was hote) but the perſon ſhall be nameles that ſlept, for that he was a knight. Though it was all done to a little diſgrace of the Gentleman: it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> (through the helpe of his ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi>) to firme vpon his head as he ſlept an huge paire of Harts horns, and as the Knight awaked thinking to pull in his head, he hit his hornes againſt the glaſſe that the panes therof flew about his eares. Thinke here how this good Gentleman was vexed, for he could neither get backward nor forward, which when the Emperor heard, all the courtiers laught, and came foorth to ſée what was happened. The Emperor alſo when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the Knight with ſo faire a head, laughed heartily thereat, and was therewithall well pleaſed: at laſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> made him quit of his hornes againe, but the Knight perceiued not how they came.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>How the aboue mentioned Knight went about to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of Doctor Fauſtus. Chap. 31.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke his leaue of the Emperor and the reſt of the Courtiers, at whoſe departure they were ſory, giuing him many rewards and guifts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but being a league and a halfe from the city, he came into a wood, where he beheld the Knight that he had i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſted with at the Court, with others in harneſſe, mounted on faire palfrayes, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with full charge towards <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> but he ſéeing their entent, ran
<pb facs="tcp:15414:28"/>towards the buſhes, and before he came amongſt the buſhes he returned againe, running as it were to méete them that chaſed him, whereupon ſodainly all the buſhes were turned into horſemen, which alſo ran to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the Knight and his company: and comming to them, they encloſed the Knight and the reſt, and told them that they muſt pay their ranſome before they departed: whereupon the Knight ſéeing himſelfe in ſuch diſtreſſe, beſought <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to be good to them, which he deitied not, but let them looſe: yet he ſo charmed them that euery one, Knight and other for the ſpace of a whole month did weare a paire of Goates hornes on their browes, and euery Palfray a paire of Oxchornes on his head, and this was their penance appointed by <hi>Fauſtus,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>Vniuerſitie requeſted Fauſtus to helpe them at a wiſh to the towne, of Menchen in Bauaria, there to ſee the Duke of Bauaria his Sonnes wedding. Chap. 32.</head>
               <p>THrée worthy yong Dukes, the which are not héere to be named, but being Students all together at the vniuerſity of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> met on a time all together, where they fell to reaſoning concerning the pompe and brauery that would be at the Cittie of <hi>Menchen</hi> in <hi>Bauaria,</hi> at the wedding of the Dukes Sonne, wiſhing themſelues there but one halfe houre to ſée the manner of their iollity: to whome one replied ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the other two Gentlemen, if it pleaſe you to giue me the heating I will giue you good counſaile that we may ſée the wedding and be here againe to night, and this is my meaning: let vs ſend to Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> make him a preſent of ſome rare thing, and ſo open our minds vnto him, deſiring him to aſſiſt vs in our enterpriſe, and aſſure ye he will not deny to fulfill our requeſt: hereupon they all concluded, ſent for <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> told him their minde, and gaue him a guift, and inuited him to a ſumptuous banquet, wherewith <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was well contented, and promiſed to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their iourney to the vttermoſt: and when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time was come that the Duke his Sonne ſhould be maryed Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> called vnto him the thrée yong Gentlemen into his houſe, commaunding them that they ſhould put on their beſt apparell, &amp; adorne themſelues as richly as they could: he tooke off his own great large cloak, went into the garden that was adioyning vnto his houſe, and ſet the thrée young Dukes on his Cloake, and he himſelfe ſate in the middeſt, but he gaue them in charge that in any wiſe they ſhould not once open their mouthes to ſpeake, or make anſwere to any man ſo ſoone as they were out, not ſo much as if the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> or his Sonne ſhould ſpeake to them or offer them courteſie they ſhould giue no word or anſwere againe: to the which they
<pb facs="tcp:15414:28"/>all agréed. Theſe conditions being made, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure: and on a ſodaine aroſe a mighty winde, heauing vp the cloake, and ſo caryed them away in the ayre, and in due time they came vnto <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen</hi> to the Dukes Court, where being entred into the vtmoſt Court the Marſhall had eſpied them, who preſently went to the Duke, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his grace that al the Lords and Gentlemen were already ſet at the table<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> notwithſtanding there were newly come thrée goodly Gentlemen with one ſeruant, the which ſtood without in the Court, wherefore the good old Duke came out vnto them welcomming them, requiring what they were, and whence? but they made no anſwere at all, whereat the Duke wondred, thinking they were all foure dumb: notwithſtanding for his honor ſake he tooke them into the court and feaſted them. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> notwithſtanding ſpake to them: if any thing happen otherwiſe then well when I ſay ſit vp, then fall you all on the cloake, and good enough: well, the water being brought, and that they muſt waſh, one of the thrée had ſo much manners as to deſire his friend to waſh firſt: which when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> heard, he ſaid, ſit vp, and all at once they got on the cloake, but he that ſpake fell off againe, the other two with Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> were againe preſently at <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> but he that remained was taken &amp; laid in priſon, wherfore the other two Gentlemen were very ſorrowfull for their friend, but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> comforted them, promiſing that on the morrow he ſhould alſo be at <hi>Wittenberg.</hi> Now all this while was the Duke ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in great feare, and ſtricken into an excéeding dump, wondring with himſelfe that his hap was ſo hard to be left behind and not the reſt: and now being weked and watched with ſo many kéepers, there were alſo certaine of the gueſts that fell to reaſoning with him to know what he was, and alſo what the other were that were vaniſhed away? but the poore priſoner thought with himſelfe, if I open what they are, then it will be euill alſo with me, whereofore all this while he gaue no man any anſwere, ſo that he was there a whole day and gaue no man a word: wherefore the old Duke gaue in charge that the next morning they ſhould racke him vntill he had confeſſed: which when the young Duke heard he began to ſorrow, and to ſay with himſelfe, it may be that to morrowe (if Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> come not to aid me) ſhall I be rached and grieuouſly tormented, inſomuch that I ſhall be conſtrained by force to tell more then willingly I would doe: but he comforted himſelfe, with hope that his friends would intreat Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> about his deline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as alſo it came to paſſe: for before it was day Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was by him, and he coniured them that watched him into ſuch a heauy ſléepe, that he with his charmes made open all the locks in the priſon, and there
<pb facs="tcp:15414:29"/>withall brought the young Duke againe in ſafety to the reſt of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes and friends, where they preſented <hi>Fauſtus</hi> with a ſumptuous guift, and ſo departed one from the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus borrowed money of a Iew, and laid his owne legge to pawne for it. Chap. 33.</head>
               <p>IT is a common Prouerb in <hi>Germany,</hi> that although a coniurer haue all things at commandement the day will come that he ſhall not be worth a peny: ſo is it like to fall out with Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> in promiſing the deuil ſo largely: and as the deuill is the author of lyes, euen ſo he led <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his minde in practiſing of things to deceiue the people, and blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them, wherin he tooke his whole delight, thereby to bring himſelfe to riches, yet notwithſtanding in the end he was neuer the richer. And although during foure and twenty yeares of his time that the deuill ſet him, he wanted nothing, yet was he beſt pleaſed when he might deceiue any body: for out of the mightieſt Potentates courts in all thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries he would ſend his ſpirit to fetch away their beſt chéere: And on a time being in his merriment where he was banquetting with other Students in an Inne, whereunto reſorted many Iewes, which when D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> perceiued, he was minded to play ſome merry ieſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a Iew, deſiring one of them to lend him ſome money for a time, the Iew was content, &amp; lent <hi>Fauſtus</hi> thréeſcore dollers for a month, which time being expired, the Iew came for his money and intreſt, but Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was neuer minded to pay the Iew againe: at length the Iew comming home to his houſe, and calling importunately for his money, doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> made him this anſwer: Iew I haue no mony, nor know I how to pay thée, but notwithſtanding to the end that thou maieſt be contented I will cut off a limme of my body, be it arme or legge, and the ſame thou ſhalt haue in pawne of thy money, yet with this condition, that when I ſhall pay thée thy mony againe, then thou ſhalt giue me my limbe. The Iew that was neuer friend to a Chriſtian, thought with himſelfe, this is a fellow right for my purpoſe, that will lay his lints to pawn for mony, and was therwith very well content: wherfore doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke a ſaw, and therwith ſéemed to cut off his leg (being not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding nothing ſo) well, he gaue it to the Iew, yet vpon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that when he got mony to pay, the Iew ſhould deliuer him his leg, to the end he might ſet it on againe. The Iew was with this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter very well pleaſed, took his leg and departed: and hauing far home, he was ſomewhat weary, and by the way he thus bethought him: what helpeth me a knaues leg? if I ſhould cary it home it would ſtinke, and ſo infect my houſe, beſides, it is too hard a péece of work to ſet it on again,
<pb facs="tcp:15414:29"/>wherefore what an aſſe was <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to lay ſo déere a pawne for ſo ſmal a ſomme of mony: and for my part quoth the Iew to himſelfe, this will neuer profite me any thing, and with theſe wordes he caſt the leg away from him into a ditch. All this Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> knew right well, therfore within thrée daies after he ſent for the Iew to make him payment of his <hi>60.</hi> dollers: the Iew came, and Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> demanded his pawne, there was his mony ready for him: the Iew anſwered, the pawne was not profitable or neceſſary for any thing, and he had caſt it away: but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> threatning, replied, I will haue my leg againe, or elſe one of thine for it. The Iew fell to intreat, promiſing him to giue him what money he would aske, if he would not deale ſtraigtly with him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Iew was conſtrained to giue him ſixty dollers more to be rid of him, and yet <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had his leg on, for he had but blinded the Iew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus deceiued a Horſe-courſer. Cap. 34.</head>
               <p>AFter the like manner he ſerued a Horſe courſer, at a Frayre called <hi>Pheiffring,</hi> for <hi>Fauſtus</hi> through his Coniuring, had got an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent faire Horſe, whereupon he rid to the Fayre, where he had many Chapmen that offred him money: laſtly he ſolde him for forty dollors, willing him that bought him, that in any wiſe he ſhould not ride him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any water, but the horſe-courſer maruelled with himſelfe that <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> had him ride him ouer no water: but (quoth he) I will proue, and foorthwith he rid him into the Riuer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> preſently the horſe vaniſhed from vnder him, and he ſate on a bottle of ſtraw, inſomuch that the man was almoſt drowned. The horſe-courſer knewe well where he lay that had ſold him his Horſe, wherefore he went angerly to his Inne, where he found Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> faſt a ſléep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſnorting on a bed, but the Horſe-courſer could no longer for beare him tooke him by the leg and began to pull him off the bed, but he pulled him ſo, that he pulled his leg from his body, inſomuch that the Horſe-courſer fell backwards in the place, then began Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to cry with an open throate, hée hath murthered me: Hereat the Horſe-courſer was afraid and gaue the ſlight, thinking none other with himſelfe but that he had pulled his leg from his body, by this meanes Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> kept his money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus eate a loade of Hay. Chap. 35.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being in a Towne of <hi>Germany</hi> called <hi>Zwickow</hi> where he was accompanyed with many Doctors and Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, and going foorth to walke after Supper, they me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te with adowne that droue a loade of Hay. Good euen good fellow, ſaid <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:15414:30"/>the clowne, what ſhall I giue thée to let me eate my belly full of hay? the clowne thought with himſelfe, what a mad man is this to eate hay, thought he with himſelfe, thou wilt not eate much: they agréed for thrée farthings he ſhould eat as much as he could: wherfore Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began to eate, and that ſo rauenouſly, that all the reſt of his company fell a laughing: blinding ſo the poore clowne, that he was ſory at his hart, for he ſéemed to haue eaten more then the halfe of his hay: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the clowne began to ſpeake him faire, for feate he ſhould haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the other halfe alſo, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> made as though he had had pitty on the clowne, and went his way. When the clowne came in place where he would be, he had his hay againe as he had before, a full loade.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus ſerued the twelue ſtudents. Chap. 36.</head>
               <p>AT <hi>Wittinberg</hi> before <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his houſe, there was a quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen ſeauen ſtudents, and fiue that came to part the reſt, one part being ſtronger then the other. Wherefore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſéeing them to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer matched, coniured them all blinde, inſomuch that the one could not ſée the other, and yet he ſo delt with them, they fought and ſmote at one another ſtill: whereat all the beholders fell a laughing: and thus they continued blind beating one another, vntill the people parted them and led each one to his owne houſe: where being entred into their houſes, they receiued their ſight perfectly againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus ſerued the drunken clownes. Chap. 37.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went into an Inne wherein were many tables full of clownes the which were tipling can after can of excellent wine: and to be ſhort they were all drunken: and as they ſat they ſo ſung and hollowed, that one could not heare a man ſpeake for them: this angred Doctor <hi>Fauſtus:</hi> wherfore he ſaid to thoſe that had called him in, marke my maiſters, I will ſhew you a merry ieſt: the clownes continuing ſtill hollowing and ſinging, he ſo coniured them, that their mouthes ſtood as wide open as it was poſſible for them to holde them, and neuer a one of them was able to cloſe his mouth again. By and by the noiſe was gone, the clownes notwithſtanding looked carneſtly one vpon another, and wiſt not what was happened: one by one they went out, and ſo ſoone as they came without, they were all as well as euer they were: but none of them deſired to goe in anymore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus ſolde fiue Swine for ſixe Dollers a peece. Chap. 38.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began another ieſt, he made him ready fiue fatte Swine, the which he ſold to one for ſixe dollers a péee, vpon this condition, that the ſwine driuer ſhould not driue them into the water:
<pb facs="tcp:15414:30"/>Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went home againe, and as the Swine had fyled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the mud, the ſwine-driuer droue them into a water, where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they were changed into ſo many bundles of ſtraw ſwimming vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in the water: the buyer looked wiſhly about him, and was ſory in his heart, but he knew not where to finde <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> ſo he was content to let all goe, and to looſe both mony and hogs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus played a merry ieſt with the Duke of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holt in his Court. Chap. 39.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> on a time came to the Duke of <hi>Anholt,</hi> who wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed him very courteouſly: this was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> month of Ianuary, where ſitting at the table, he perceiued the Ducheſſe to be with childe, and forbearing himſelfe vntill the meat was taken from the table, and that they brought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> banquetting diſhes, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid to the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, gracious Lady, I haue alwaies heard that great bellied women doe alwaies long for ſome dainties, I beſéech therefore your grace hide not your mind from me, but tell me what you deſire to eat? ſhe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> now truly I will not hide from you what my heart doth moſt deſire, namely, that if it were now harueſt I would cat my belly full of grapes, and other dainty fruite: Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hereupon, Gratious Lady, this is a ſmall thing for me to doe, for I can doe more then this: wherefore he tooke a plate, and ſet open one of the Cazements of the Window, holding it forth, where incontinent he had his diſh full of all manner of fruite, as red and white Grapes, Peares and Apples, the which came from out of ſtrange countries: all theſe he preſented the Ducheſſe, ſaying: Madam I pray you vouchſafe to taſt of this dainty fruit, the which came from a farre countrie, for there the ſummer is not yet ended. The Dutches thanked <hi>Fauſtus</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſhe fell to her fruit with full appetite. The Duke of <hi>Anholt</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding could not withhold to aſke <hi>Fauſtus</hi> with what reaſon there were ſuch young fruit to be had at that time of the yeare. Doctor <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> told him, may it pleaſe your grace to vnderſtand, that the yeare is diuided into two circles ouer the whole world that when with vs it is winter, in the contrary circle it is notwithſtanding ſummer, for in <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Saba</hi> there falleth or ſetteth the ſun, ſo that it is ſo warme that they haue twiſe a yeare fruit: and gracious Lord I haue a ſwift ſpirit, the which can in the twinckling of an eye fulfill my deſire in any thing, wherefore I ſent him into thoſe countries, who hath brought this fruit as you ſee: whereat the Duke was in great admiration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus through his charmes made a great Caſtle in preſence of the Duke of Anholt. Chap. 40.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:31"/>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> deſired the Duke of <hi>Anholt</hi> to walke a little forth of the Court with him, wherefore they went together into the field, where Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> (through his ſki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l) had placed a mightie Caſtle, which when the Duke ſaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, he wondred thereat, ſo did the Dutcheſſe, and all the beholders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that on that Hill which is called the <hi>Rohumbuel,</hi> ſhould on the ſuddain be ſo faire a Caſtle. At laſt, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> deſired the Duke and the Dutcheſſe to walke with him into the Caſtle, which they denyed not. This Caſtle was ſo wonderfull ſtrong, hauing about it a great and déep trench of water, the which was full of fiſh, and all manner of water-foules, as Swannes, Duckes, Gooſe, Bitters, and ſuch like. About the wall, was fine ſtone do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and two other dores: alſo within, was a great open Court, wherein were inchaunted, all manner of wilde Beaſts, ſpecially ſuch as were not to be found in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> as Apes, Beares, Buffes, Antelops, and many other ſtrange Beaſtes. Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, there were Hartes, Hurdes, Roe buckes and Does and wilde Soome: All manner of land-Fowle that any man could think on, which flewe from one tree to an other. After all this, he ſet his gueſts to the Table, being the Duke and Dutcheſſe, with all their traine, for he had prouided them a moſt ſump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uous Fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, both of meat, and alſo of any kind of drinke: for he ſet nine Meſſe of meat v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on the boord at once, and all this muſt his <hi>Wagner</hi> doe, to place all thinges on the boord, the which was brought vnto him by the ſpirit, inuiſible, of all thinges their hartes could deſire, as wild-foule, veniſon, and all manner of dayntie Fiſh that could be thought on: of wine alſo great plenty, and of diuers ſortes, as <hi>French</hi> wine, <hi>Cullen</hi> wine, <hi>Crabaſhir</hi> wine, <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> wine, <hi>Spauiſh</hi> wine, <hi>Hungarian</hi> wine, <hi>Watzburg</hi> wine, <hi>Malmeſey,</hi> &amp; Sacke: In the whole, there were a <hi>100</hi> Cans ſtanding round about the houſe. This ſumptuous banquet, the Duke took thankfully, and afterwards he departed homewards, and to their thinking they had neither eaten or drunke: ſo were they blinded while they were in the Caſtle. But as they were in their Pallace, they looked towards the Caſtle, and beheld it all on a flame of fire, and all thoſe which ſaw it, wondred to heare ſo ſtrange anoyſe, as if it had bene great Ordnance ſhould haue bene ſhot off: and thus the Caſtle burned, &amp; conſumed away cleaue. Which done, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> raturned to the Duke, who gaue him great thankes for ſhewing them ſo great curteſie, and gaue him a hundred dollors, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to departe, or ſtay there at his owne diſcretion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus with his Company, viſited the Biſhop of Saltzburgs Wine-Celler. Chap. 41.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:31"/>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hauing taken leaue of the Duke, he went to <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,</hi> néere about Shroue tide, and being in company with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtudents, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was himſelfe the God of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> who hauing well feaſted the Students before with dainty fare, after the manner of <hi>Germany,</hi> where it is counted no feaſt except all the bidden gueſts be drunke, which Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> intanding, ſaid: Gentlemen, and my gueſts, will it pleaſe you to take a cup of Wine with me in a place or Celler whereunto I will bring you: they all ſaid willingly we will: which when Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> heard he tooke them forth, ſet either of them vpon an Holly wand, and ſo was coniured into the Biſhop of <hi>Saltzburg</hi> his Celler, for there about grew excellent pleaſant Wine: there fell <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and his company to drinking and ſwilling, not of the worſt but of the beſt. And as they were merry in the celler, came downe to draw drinke the Biſhops Butler: which when he perceiued ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons there, he cryed with a loude voyce, théeues théeues. This ſpited Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> wonderfully, wherfore he made euery one of his company to ſit on their holly wand, &amp; ſo vaniſhed away: and in parting D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke the butler by the haire of the head, and carried him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with them vntill they came to a mighty high lopped trée, and on the top of that huge tree he ſet the Butler: where he remained in a moſt fearefull perplexitie: D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> departed to his houſe, where they tooke their <hi>valete</hi> one of another, drinking the wine the which they had ſteine in great bottels of glaſſe out of the Biſhops celler. The Butler that had helo himſelfe by the hands vpon the lopped trée all the night, was almoſt frozen with colde, eſpying the day, and ſéeing the trée of ſo huge great gighnes, thought with himſelfe it is vnpoſſible to come off this trée without perill of death; at length he eſpied certaine clownes which were paſſing by, he cried, for the loue of God helpe me down, the clownes ſeeing him ſo high, wondred what mad man would clime to ſo huge a trée, wherefore as a thing moſt miraculous, they caryed tydings to the biſhop of <hi>Saltzburg:</hi> then was there great running on euery ſide to ſee him in the trée, and many deuiſes they practiſed ſo get him downe with ropes: and being demanded by the Biſhop how he came there, he ſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was brought thither by the haire of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of certaine the nes that were robbing of the wine celler, but what they were he knew not, for (ſaid he) they had faces like men, but they wrought like Diuels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus kept his Chroue-tide. Chap. 42.</head>
               <p>THere were ſeuen ſtudents and maſters that ſtudied Diuinity, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris prudentia &amp; medicina,</hi> all theſe hauing conſented, were ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad to viſit Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> and to celebrate Shro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>de with him: who
<pb facs="tcp:15414:32"/>being come to his houſe, he gaue them their welcome, for they were his déere friends, deſiring them to ſit downe, where he ſerued them with a very good ſupper of Mens, fiſh and other roſt, yet were they but ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chéered: wherefore Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> comforted his gueſts, excuſing himſelfe that they ſtole vpon him ſo ſuddainly, that he had not leyſure to prouide for them ſo well as they were worthy: but my good friends (quoth he) according to the vſe of our Country, we muſt drinke all this night &amp; ſo a draught of the beſt wine to bedward is commendable. For you know that in great Potentates courts they vſe as this night great feaſting, the like will I doe for you: for I haue thrée great flaggens of Wine, the fieſt is full of Hungarian Wine, containing eight gallons, the ſecond of Italian Wine contaning ſeuen gallons, the third contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſixe gallons of Spaniſh wine, all the which we will tipple out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be day: beſides, we haue fiftéene diſhes of meate, the which my ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> hath fette ſo farre, that it was colde before hée brought it, and they are all full of the daintieſt thinges that ones heart can deuiſe, but (ſaith <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) I muſt make them hote againe, and you may beléeue me Gentlemen, that this is no blinding of you, whereas you thinke that it is no natural food, verily it is as good and as pleaſant as euer you eate. And hauing ended his tale, he commaunded his boy to lay the cloath, which done, he ſerued them with fiftéene meſſe of meate, hauing thrée diſhes to a meſſe, the which were all manner of Veniſon, and dainty wild fowle, and for wine there was no lacke, as Italian wine, Hungarian wine, and Spaniſh wine: and when they were all made drunke, and that they had almoſt eaten all their good cheere, they began to ſing and to dance vntill it was day, and then they departed euery one to his owne habitation at whoſe parting, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them to be his gueſts againe the next day following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus feaſted his gueſts on the Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wedneſday. Chap. 43.</head>
               <p>VPon Aſh wedneſday came vnto Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his bidden gueſts the Students, whom he feaſted very royally, inſomuch that they were all full and luſtie, dauncing and ſinging as the night before: and when the high glaſſes and goblets were carouſed one to another doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began to play them ſome pretty feates, inſomuch that round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the hall was heard moſt pleaſant muſick, &amp; that in ſundry places: in this corner a Lute in another corner a Cornet, in another a Cithern, Clarigolds, Harpe, Horne-pipe: in fine, all manner of Muſicke was heard there at that inſtant, whereat all the glaſſes and goblets, cups, and pots, diſhes, and all that ſtoods on the boord began to daunce: then
<pb facs="tcp:15414:32"/>Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tooke ten ſtone pots, and ſet them downe on the floore where preſently they began to dance, and to ſmite one againſt the other that the ſhiuers flew round about the whole houſe, whereat the whole company fell a laughing. Then he began another ieſt, he ſet an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the table, and cauſed a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous great Ape to come in amongſt them, which Ape began to dance and to ſkip, ſhewing them many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conceits. In this and ſuch like paſtime they paſſed away the whole day, where night being come, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> bad them all to Supper, which they lightly agréed vnto, for Students in theſe caſes are eaſily intreated: wherefore he promiſed to feaſt them with a banket of fowle, and afterward they would goe all about with a mask: then D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> put forth a long pole out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> window, wherupon preſently there came innumerable of birds &amp; wild fowle, and ſo many as came, had not any power to flie away againe, but he tooke them and flang them to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, who lightly pulled of the neckes of them, and being roaſted they made their ſupper: which being ended, they made themſelues ready to the mask. Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> commanded euery one to put on a cleane ſhirt ouer his other cloaths, which being done, they looked one vpon another, it ſéemed to each one of them they had no heads, and ſo they went forth vnto certaine of their neighbours, at which ſight the people were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully afraid. And as the vſe of <hi>Germany</hi> is, that wherſoeuer a mask entreth, the good man of the houſe muſt feaſt them: ſo when theſe maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers were ſet to their banquet, they ſéemed againe in their former ſhape with heads, inſomuch that they were all knowne what they were, and hauing ſate and well eate and drunke, D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> made that euery one had an Aſſes head on, with great and long eares, ſo they fell to dancing and to drine away the time vntill it was midnight, and then euery man departed home: and aſſoone as they were out of the houſe, each one was in his naturall ſhape againe, and ſo they ended and went to ſléepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus the day following was feaſted of the ſtudents, and of his merry ieſts with them while he was in their company. Chap. 44.</head>
               <p>THe laſt <hi>Bacchanal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was held on Thurſday, where inſued a great ſnow, and D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was inuited vnto the Students that were with him the day before, where they had prepared an excellent banket for him, which banket being ended, doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> began to play his old pranks, and forthwith were in the place thirtéen Apes, that tooke hands and danced round in a ring together, then they ſell to tumbling &amp; vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r another, that it was moſt pleaſent to beheld, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of the window and vaniſhed away: then they ſet before Doctor
<pb facs="tcp:15414:33"/>
                  <hi>Fauſtus</hi> a roaſted calues head, which one of the Students cut a péece of, and laid it on Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his trencher, which péece being no ſooner laid downe, but the Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes head began to cry mainly out like a man, murther, murther, out alas what doſt thou to me? whereat they were all amazed, but after a while, conſidering of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his teſting tucks, they began to laugh, and then they pulled in ſunder the calues head, and cate it vp, Whereupon Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> asked leane to depart, but they would in no wiſe agrée to let him goe, except that he would promiſe to come again preſently: then <hi>Fauſtus</hi> through his cunning made a fledge the which was drawne about the houſe with foure firy dragons: this was fearefull for the ſtudents to beholde, for they ſaw <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ride vp and downe as though he ſhould haue fired and ſlaine all them in the houſe. This ſport continued vntil midnight, with ſuch a noiſe that they could not heare one another, and the heads of the ſtudents were ſo light that they thought themſelues to be in the ayre all that time,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus ſhewed the faire Helena vnto the ſtudents vpon the Sunday following. Chap. 45.</head>
               <p>THe Sunday following came thoſe ſtudents home to Doctor <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> his owne houſe, and brought their meat and drinke with them, theſe men were right welcome gueſts vnto <hi>Fauſtus</hi> wherefore they all fell to drinking wine ſmoothly: and being merry, they began ſome of them to talke of the beauty of women, and euery one gaue forth his verdit what he had ſéene, and what he had heard: So one among the reſt ſaid, I neuer was ſo deſirous of any thing in this world, as to haue a ſight (if it were poſſible) of faire <hi>Helena</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> for whom the worthy towne of <hi>Troy</hi> was deſtroyed and razed downe to the ground, therefore, ſaith he, that in all mens iudgement ſhe was more then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly faire, becauſe that when ſhe was ſtolne away from her husband, there was for her recouery ſo great bloodſhed.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered: for that you are all my friends, and are ſo deſirous to ſée that ſtately pearle of <hi>Greece,</hi> faire <hi>Helena,</hi> the wife of King <hi>Menelaus</hi> and daughter of <hi>Tendalus</hi> and <hi>Leda,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> who was the faireſt Lady in all <hi>Greece:</hi> I will therefore bring her into your preſence perſonally and in the ſame forme of attire as ſhe vſed to goe when ſhe was in her chiefeſt flowers, and pleaſanteſt pria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of youth. The like haue I done for the Emperour <hi>Carolus Magnus,</hi> at his deſire I ſhewed him <hi>Alexander</hi> the great and his Paramout: but (ſaid Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) I charge you all that vpon your perils you ſpeake not a word, nor riſe vp from the table ſo long as ſhe is in your preſence. And ſo he went out of the hall, returning preſently againe: after whom
<pb facs="tcp:15414:33"/>immediatly folowed the faire and beautiful <hi>Helena,</hi> whoſe beauty was ſuch that the ſtudents were all amazed to ſée her, eſteeming her rather to be a heauenly then an earthly Creature: This Lady appeared before them in a moſt rich Gowne of purple Velnet, coſily imbroadred: her haire hanged downe looſe, as fairs as the beaten golde, and of ſuch len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth, that it reached downe to her h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmes, hauing moſt amorous cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> eyes, a ſwéet &amp; pleaſant round ace, with lips as red as a Cherry, he chéeks of a roſe colour, her mouth ſmall, her neck white like a ſwan, tall &amp; ſlender of perſonage In ſumme, there was no imperfect place in her: ſhe looked round about with a rolling Haukes eye a ſmiling and wanton countenance, which nere hand inflamd the harts of al ſtudents, but that they perſwaded themſelues ſhe was a ſpirit, which made them lightly paſſe away ſuch fancyes: and thus faice <hi>Helen</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went out againe one with an an other. But the ſtudents, at <hi>Fauſtus</hi> entring into the Hall againe, requeſted him to let them ſee her againe the next day, for that they would bring with them a Painter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to take her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet: which he denyed, affirming that he could not alwayes raiſe vp her ſpirit, but onely at certaine tunes: yet ſaid he, I will gine you her Counterfet, which ſhall be as good to you, as if your ſelfe ſhould ſée the drawing therof, which they receiued according to his promiſe, but ſoone loſt it againe. The ſtudents departed from <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to their ſeueral lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, but none of them could ſleep that night, for thinking on the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of faire <hi>Hellen.</hi> Therfore a man may ſée, that the deuill blindeth and inflameth the hart oft times with luſt, that men fall in in loue with har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, wherby their mindes can afterwards be hardly remoued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus Coniured away the foure wheeles from a Clownes Waggon. Chap. 46.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was ſent for, to come to the Marſhall of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> who was maruailouſly troubled with the falling ſickeneſſe: Now <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had this quality, he ſildome rid, but walkt on foote, to eaſe himſelfe when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e liſt: And as he came néere vnto the Towne of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> there ouertooke him a Clowne with foure horſes and an empty Waggon: to whome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> (ieſtingly to try him) ſaid vnto him, I pray thée good fellow let mer dea little to eaſe my weary leggs, which the buſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dly Aſſe denyes, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving, that his horſes were all weary: and he woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not let him get vp: Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> did this but to prooue this Clowne if there were any c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtery to be found in him if need were: But ſuch churliſhnes is commonly found among Clownes but he was well requited by <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> euen with the like payment, for pe ſaid vnto
<pb facs="tcp:15414:34"/>him. Thou doltiſh clowne, voyd of all humility, ſéeing thou art of ſo currith diſpoſition I will pay thée as thou haſt deſerued: for the foure wheeles of thy Wagon thou ſhalt haue taken from thée, let me ſée then how thou canſt ſhift: hereupon his whéeles were gone, his horſes alſo fell downe to the ground as though they had béene dead: whereat the clowne was ſore afrighted, meaſuring it a iuſt ſcourge of God for his ſinnes and churliſhnes, wherfore all trembling and wailing, he humbly beſought Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to be good vnto him, confeſſing he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it, notwithſtanding if it pleaſed him to forgiue him, he would herafter doe better. Which humility made <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his heart to repent, anſwering him on this maner: Well doe ſo no more, but when a poore man deſireth thée, ſée that thou let him ride, but yet thou ſhalt not goe altogether cléere, for although thou haue againe thy foure whéeles, yet ſhalt thou fetch them at the foure gates of the City, ſo he threw duſt on the horſes and reuiued them againe, and the Clowne for his churliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was faine to fetch his whéeles, ſpending his time with wearines, whereas before he might haue done a good déede, and gone about his buſines quietly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>How foure Iuglers cut one anothers head off, and ſet them on againe and how Doctor Fauſtus deceiued them. Chap. 47.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> came in the Lent vnto Frankford fayre, where his Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> gaue him to vnderſtand that in an Inne were foure Iuglers that cut one anothers head off, and after their cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off ſent them to the barber to be trimmed, which many people ſaw. This angred <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> for he meant to haue himſelfe the onely Cocke in the deuills baſket, and he went to the place where they were to behold them. And as theſe Iuglers were together ready one to cut off anothers head, there ſtood alſo the barbers ready to trim them, and by them vpon the table ſtood likewiſe a glaſſe full of ſtilled water, and he that was the chiefeſt amongſt them ſtood by it. Thus they began, they ſmote off the bead of the firſt, &amp; preſently there was a Lilly in the glaſſe of diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led water, where <hi>Fauſtus</hi> perceiuing this Lilly as it was ſpringing, and the chiefe Iugler named it the trée of life, thus dealt he with the firſt, making the barber waſh and comb his head, and then he ſet it on again, preſently the Lilly vaniſhed away out of the water, hereat the man had his head whole and ſound againe, the like did they with the other two: and as the turne and lot came to the chiefe Iugler that he alſo ſhould be beheaded, &amp; that this Lilly was moſt pleaſant, faire, &amp; floriſhing gréene, they ſmote his head off, &amp; when it came to be barbed, it troubled <hi>Fauſtus</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15414:34"/>his conſcience, inſomuch that he could not abide to ſée another doe any thing, for he thought himſelfe to be the principal Coniurer in the world: wherefore Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went to the table whereas the other Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers kept that Lilly, and ſo he tooke a ſmall knife and cut off the ſtalke of the Lilly, ſaying to himſelfe, none of them ſhould blinde <hi>Fauſtus:</hi> yet no man ſaw <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to cut the Lilly, but when the reſt of the Iuglers thought to haue ſet on their maiſters head, they could not, wherefore they looked on the Lilly, and found it bléeding, by this meanes the Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler was beguiled, and ſo dyed in his wickedues, yet not one thought that Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had done it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <head>How an olde man the neighbour of Fauſtus ſought to perſwade him to amend his euill life and to fall vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Chap. 48.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Good Chriſtian, an honeſt and vertuous olde man a louer of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly Scriptures, who was neighbour vnto D. <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> when he perceiued that many ſtudents had their recourſe in and out vnto Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> he ſuſpected his euill life, wherefore like a friend he inuited Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> to ſupper vnto his houſe, to the which he agréed: and hauing ended their banquet, the olde man began with theſe words: My louing friend and neighbour Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> I am to deſire of you a friendly and a hri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tan requeſt, beſeeching you that you will vouchſafe not to be angry with me, but friendly reſolue me in my doubt and take my poore inuiting in good part. To whom D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered: my louing neighbour, I pray you ſay your mind. Then began the olde Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron to ſay: My good neighbour, you know in the beginning how that you haue defied God, and all the hoaſt of Heauen, and giuen your ſoule to the diuell, wherewith you haue incurred Gods high diſpleaſure, and are become fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Chriſtian, far worſe then a heathen perſon: oh conſider what you haue done, it is not only the pleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, but that ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſoule that you muſt haue reſpect vnto: of which if you be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, then are you caſt away, and ſhall remaine in the anger of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. But yet it is time enough D. <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> if you repent and call vnto the Lord for mercy, as we haue example in the Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles the <hi>8.</hi> Chap. of <hi>Simon</hi> in <hi>Samaria,</hi> who tras<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed out of the way, affirming that he was <hi>Simon homo Sanctus.</hi> This m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n was notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the end conuerted, after that he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſermon of <hi>Philip,</hi> for he was baptized and ſaw his ſinne and repented. Likewiſe I beſéech you good bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t my rude ſermon be vnto you a conuertion: and forget the filthy life that yet hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ledd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ezent, aske mercy, and liue: for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Come vnto me all ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:15414:35"/>weary, and heauy laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> And in <hi>Ezechiel, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he will conuert and liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let my wordes good Brother <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> pierce into your Adamant heart, and deſire God for his ſon Chriſt his ſake to forgiue you. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue you ſo long liued in your diueliſh practiſes, knowing that in the olde and new teſtament you are forbidden, and that men ſhould not ſuffer any ſuch to liue, neither haue any conuerſation with them, for it is an abhomination vnto the Lord: and that ſuch perſons haue no part in the Kingdome of God. All this while Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> heard him very attentiuely, and replyed. Father your perſwaſions like me wondrous well, and I thanke you with all my heart for your good will and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſing you as farre as I may to allow your diſcipline: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he tooke his leaue. And being come home, he lay him very penſiue on his bed, bethinking himſelfe of the wordes of the olde man, and in a manner began to repent that he had giuen his ſoule to the diuell, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to deny all he had promiſed to <hi>Lucifer.</hi> Continuing in theſe cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ſuddainly his ſpirit appeared vnto him clapping him vpon the head: and wrung it as though he would haue pulled his head from his ſhaulders ſaying vnto him: Thou knoweſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy ſelfe, body and ſoule, to my Lord <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and thou haſt vowed thy ſelfe an enemy to God and vnto all men, and now thou beginneſt to hearken vnto an olde doting foole which perſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth thée as it were vnto good when indéed it is too lace, for that thou art the Diuels, and he hath good power preſently to fetch thée: wherefore he hath ſent me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, to tell thée, that ſéeing thou haſt ſorrowed for that thou haſt done, begin againe and write another writing with thine owne blood, if not, then will I teare thée all to péeces. Hereat Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was ſore afraid and ſaid: My <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> I will write againe what thou wilt: wherefore he ſate him downe, and with his owne blood he wrote as followeth: which writing was afterward ſent to a deare friend of the ſaid Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> being his kinſ-man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus, wrote the ſecond time with his owne blood and gaue it to the deuill. Chap. 49.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Doctor <hi>Iohn Fauſtus,</hi> acknowledge by this my déed and hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that ſith my firſt writing, which is ſeuentéen yeares, that I haue right willingly held, and hath béen an vtter enemy vnto God &amp; all men, the which I once againe confirme, and giue fully and wholy my ſelfe vnto the deuill both body and ſoule, euen vnto the great <hi>Lucifer,</hi> &amp; that at the end of ſeauen yeares inſuing after the date of this letter, he ſhall haue to doe with me according as it pleaſeth him, either to lengthen or
<pb facs="tcp:15414:35"/>ſhorten my life as pleaſeth him: and hereupon I renounce all perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that ſéeke to withdraw me from my purpoſe by the word of God, either ghoſtly or bodily: and further, I wil neuer giue eare vnto any man be he ſpirituall or temporall, that moueth any matter for the ſaluation of my ſoule. Of all this writing, and that therein conteined, be witnes my bloud, the which with my hands I haue begun and ended.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dated at VVittenberg</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>the 25. of Iuly.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>And preſently vpon the making of this letter, he became ſo great an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the poore old man, that he ſought his life by all meanes poſſible, but this godly man was ſtrong in the holy Ghoſt that he could not be vanquiſhed by any meanes, for about two dayes after that he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> as the poore man lay in his bed, ſuddainly there was a mighty rumbling in the chamber, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he was neuer wont to heare, and he heard as it had béene the groaning of a Sow, which laſted long: whereupon the good old man began to ieſt and mocke, and ſaid: oh what Barbarian cry is this: oh faire bird, what ſoule muſick is this? a faire Angell, that could not tary two daies in his place? beginneſt thou now to rim into a poore mans houſe, where thou haſt no power, and wert not able to kéepe thy owne two dayes? With theſe and ſuch like words the ſpirit departed. And when he came home, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> asked him how hée had ſped with the olde man? to whome the ſpirit anſwered, the olde man was harneſſed, and that he could not once lay holde vpon him: but hée would not tell how the olde man had mocked him, for the Diuels can neuer abide to heare of their fall. Thus doth God defend the hearts of all honeſt Chriſtians, that be take themſelues vnder his tuition.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus made a marriage between two louers. Cap. 50.</head>
               <p>IN the Citty of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> was a Student, a gallant Gentleman, named <hi>N. N.</hi> This Gentleman was farre in loue with a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, faire and proper of perſonage: This Gentlewoman had a knight that was a ſuter vnto her, and many other Gentlemen the which deſired her in mariage, but none could obtain her: ſo it was that this <hi>N.N.</hi> was very well acquainted with <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> and by that meanes became a ſuter vnto him to aſſiſt him in the matter, for he fell ſo farre in diſpaire with himſelfe, that he pined away to the skin and bones, But when he had opened the matter vnto Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> he asked counſell of his ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> the which tolde him what to doe. Hereupon Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> went home to the Gentleman and bad him be of good chéere, for he ſhould haue his deſire, for he would helpe him to that he wiſhed for, and that this Gentlewoman ſhould loue none other but him onely, wherefore D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſo changed the mind of the damſell by a practiſe
<pb facs="tcp:15414:36"/>he wrought, that ſhe ſhould doe no other thing but think on him whom before ſhe had hated, neither cared ſhe for any man but him alone. The deuice was thus: <hi>Fauſtus</hi> commaunded the Gentleman that he ſhould cloath himſelfe in all the beſt apparell that he had, and that he ſhould goe vnto this Gentlewoman, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſhowe himſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> giuing him a King, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding him in any wiſe that he ſhould daunce with her before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: who folowing his Counſel, went to her, and when they began to daunce, they that were ſuiters began to take euery one his Lady by the hand: this Gentleman tooke her woo before had ſo diſdayned him, and in the daunce, he put the King into her hand that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> had giuen him, which ſhe no ſooner toucht, but ſhe fell preſently in loue with him, ſmiling at him in the daunce, and many times winking at him, rolling her eyes, and in the end ſhe aſked him if be could loue her, and make her his wife? he gladly anſwered, that he was content: whereupon they concluded, and were maryed, by the meanes and help of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> for the which, the Gentleman will rewarded hun.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus, led his friends into his Garden at Chriſtmas, and ſhowed them many ſtrange ſights, in his ninteenth yeare. Chap. 51.</head>
               <p>IN December, about Chriſtmas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the City of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Gentlemen which were come out of the Country to be merry with their friends: amongſt whome, there were certaine well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> who often inuited them home vnto his houſes they being there on a certaine time, after dinner he had them into his Garden, where they beheld all maner of flowers and freſh hearbes, and trées bearing fruit and bloſſomes of all ſortes, who wondred to ſée that his garden ſhould ſo flouriſh at that time, as in the midſt of Sommer: and abroad in the ſtreets and all the countrey lay full of ſnowe and yee: Wherefore this was noted of them, as a thing miraculous: euery one gathering and carying away, all ſuch thinges as they beſt liked, and ſo departed, delight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with their ſwéet ſmelling flowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus, gathered together, a great Army of men, in his extremity, againſt a Knight that would haue miured him on his iourney. Chap. 52.</head>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> trauayld towards <hi>Eyzelben,</hi> and when he was nigh halfe the way, he eſpyed ſeuen horſe-men, and the chiefe of them be knewe to be the Knight with whome he had Ieſted in the Emperours Court: for he had ſet a huge payre of Harts hornes vpon his head, and when the Knight now ſawe that he had fit oportunity to be reuenged of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> he ran vpon him (and thoſe that were with him) to miſchiefe
<pb facs="tcp:15414:36"/>him, intending priuile to ſlay him: which when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> eſpyed, he vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away into a wood which was hard by them: But when the Knight perceiued that he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vaniſhed away, he cauſed his men to ſtand ſtill, but where they remained, they heard all maner of warlike Inſtruments of muſick, as Drums, Flutes, Trumpets, and ſuch like, and a certaine troope of horſ-men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing toward them: then they turned another way, and they were alſo met on that ſide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another way, &amp; yet were freſhly aſſaulted, ſo that which way ſo euer they turned themſelues, he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred, inſomuch that when the Knight perceiued that he could eſcape no way, but that they his enemies laid on him which way ſoeuer hée offered to flye, hée tooke a good heart, and ran amongſt the thickeſt, and thought with himſelfe, better to dye then to liue with ſo great an infamy. Therefore being at handy blowes with them he demanded the cauſe why they ſhould ſo vſe him? but none of them would giue him anſwer vntill Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhewed himſelfe vnto the Knight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they incloſed him round, and Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid vnto him ſir, yéeld your weapon, and your ſelfe, other wiſe it will goe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with you. The Knight knew no other but that he was inuironed with an hoaſt of men (where indeed they were none other th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n diuels) yéelded: then <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> tooke away his ſword, his péece, and horſe, with all the reſt of his companions. And further he ſaid vnto him, Sir: the chiefe Generall of our army hath commaunded to deale with you according to the Law of Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall depart in peace whither you pleaſe, and then he gaue the Knight a horſe after the manner, and ſet him thereon, ſo he rode, the reſt went on foote, vntill they came to their Inne, where being alighted, his Page rode on his horſe to the water, and preſently the horſe vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away, the Page being almoſt ſunke and drowned, but he eſcaped, and comming home, the Knight perceiued his Page ſo bemyred and on foote, asked where his horſe was become: who anſwered that he was vaniſhed away: which when the Knight heard, hee ſaid, of a truth this is <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his doing, for he ſerueth me now as he did before at the Court, onely to make me a ſcorne and a laughing ſtocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus cauſed Mephoſtophiles to bring him 7. of the faireſt women he could finde in all the Countries he had trauailed in, in the 20 yeare. Chap. 53.</head>
               <p>WHen D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> called to minde that his time from day to day drew nigh, he began to liue a ſwini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h &amp; epicuriſh life, wherefore he commaunded his Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> to bring him ſeauen of the
<pb facs="tcp:15414:37"/>faireſt women that he had ſeene in all the time of his trauell: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought, firſt one, then another, he lay with them all, inſomuch that he liked them ſo well, that he continued with them in all manner of loue and made them to trauell with him in all his iourners: Theſe women were <hi>2. Netherlands, 1. Hungarian, 1. Engliſh, 2. Wallons, 1. Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander:</hi> and with theſe ſwéet perſonages he continued long, yea euen to his laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus found a maſſe of money, when he had conſumed 22. of his yeares. Chap. 54.</head>
               <p>TO the end that the Diuell would make <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his onely heire, hée ſhewed vnto him, where he ſhould goe and finde a mighty huge maſſe of money, and that he ſhould haue it in an olde Chappell that was fallen downe: halfe a mile diſtant from <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> there he had him to dig, and ſhould finde it, the which he did, and hauing digged reaſonable déep, he ſaw a mighty huge ſerpent, the which lay on the treaſure it ſelfe, the treaſure it ſelfe lay like a huge light burning: but Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> charmed the Serpent that he crept into a hole, and when he digged dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to get vp the treaſure, he found nothing but coales of fire: there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he heard and ſaw many that were tormented, yet notwithſtanding he brought away the coales, and when he was come home: it was all turned into ſiluer and gold, and after his death it was found by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, the which was almoſt about eſtimation a thouſand Gilders.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus made the ſpirit of faire Helena of Greece his owne Paramour and bedfellow in his 23. yeare. Chap. 55.</head>
               <p>TO the end that this miſerable <hi>Fauſtus</hi> might fill the luſt of his fleſh, and liue in all manner of voluptuous pleaſures, it came in his mind after he had ſlept his firſt ſléepe, and in the <hi>23.</hi> yeare paſt of his time, that he had a great deſire to lye with faire <hi>Helena</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> eſpecially her whome he had ſéene and ſhewed vnto the ſtudents at <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> wherefore he called vnto his ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles,</hi> commanding him to bring him the faire <hi>Helena,</hi> which he alſo did, wherupon he fell in loue with her, and made her his common concubine, and bedfellow, for ſhe was ſo beautifull and delightfull a péece, that he could not be one houre from her, if he ſhould therfore haue ſuffred death, ſhe had ſo ſtolue away his heart, and to his ſéeming in time ſhe was with childe, and in the end brought him a man childe, whom <hi>Fauſtus</hi> named <hi>Iuſtus Fauſtus:</hi> This child tolde D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> many things that were to come, and what ſtrange things were done in forraine Countries: but in the end when <hi>Fauſtus</hi> loſt his life, the mother and the childe vaniſhed away both together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus made his will, in which he named his ſeruant Wagner to be his heire. Chap. 56.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:15414:37"/>
               <p>DOctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was now in this <hi>24.</hi> and laſt yeare, and hée had a pretty ſtripling to his ſeruant, the which had ſtudied alſo at the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſity of <hi>Wittenberg:</hi> this youth was very well acquainted with his knaueries and ſorceries ſo that he was hated aſwell for his owne kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, as alſo for his maiſters: for no man would giue him entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into his ſeruice, becauſe of his vnhappineſſe, but <hi>Fauſtus:</hi> This <hi>Wagner</hi> was ſo well brioued with <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that he vſed him as his ſon: for doe what he would, his maſter was alwayes therewith well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And when the time drew nigh that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſhould end, hée called vnto him a Notary and certaine Maiſters, the which were his friends, and often conuerſant with him, in whoſe proſence he gaue this <hi>Wagner</hi> his houſe and garden. Item he gaue him in ready money <hi>16000.</hi> Gilders. Item a Farme. Item a Gold chaine, much Plate, and other houſhold ſtuffe. That gaue he all to his ſeruant and the reſt of his time he meant to ſpend in Innes and Students company, drinking and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, with other iollitie: and thus he finiſhed his will for that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus fell in talke with his ſeruant touching his Teſtament, and the couenants thereof. Chap. 57.</head>
               <p>NOw when his will was made Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> called vnto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, ſaying, I haue thought vpon thée in my Teſtament, for that thou haſt béene a truſty ſeruant vnto me, and a faithfull, and haſt not opened my ſecrets, and yet further (ſaid he) aske of me before I die what thou wilt and I will giue it vnto thée. His ſeruant raſhly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I pray you let me haue your cunning. To which Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered I haue giuen thée all my books, vpon this condition that thou wouldſt not let them be common, but vſe them for thine owne pleaſure, and ſtudy carefully in them. And doſt thou alſo deſire my cunning? That maiſt thou peraduenture haue, if thou loue and peruſe my bookes well. Further (ſaid Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) ſéeing that thou deſireſt of me this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, I will reſolue thée: my Spirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> his time is out with me, and I haue nought to command him as touching thée, yet wil I helpe thée to another if thou like well therof. And within three dayes after he called his ſeruent vnto him, ſaying, art thou reſolued: wouldſt thou verily haue a ſpirit: Then tell me in what manner or forme thou wouldſt haue him: To whom his ſeruant anſwered, that he would haue him in the forme of an Ape: whereupon appeared preſently a Spirit vnto him in manner and forme of an Ape, the which leaped about the houſe. Then ſaid <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſée, there haſt thou thy requeſt, but yet he will not obey thee vntill I be dead, for when my ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> ſhall fetch me away, then ſhall thy ſpirit be bound vnto thée, if thou agree: and
<pb facs="tcp:15414:38"/>thy Spirit ſhalt thou name <hi>Abercocke:</hi> for ſo he is called: but all this is vpon condition that you publiſh my cunning and my merry conceits: with all that I haue done (when I am dead) in an hiſtorie: and if thou canſt not remember all, the ſpirit <hi>Abercocke</hi> will helpe thée: ſo ſhall the great acts that I haue done be manifeſt vnto the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus hauing but one month of his appointed time to come, fell to mourning and ſorrow with himſelfe, for his diueiliſh exerciſe. Chap. 58.</head>
               <p>TIme ran away with <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> as the houre-glaſſe, for he had but one month to come of his <hi>24.</hi> yeares, at the end whereof he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen himſelfe to the diuell body and ſoule, as it is before ſpecified. Here was the firſt token for hée was like a taken murtherer, or a theefe, the which findeth himſelfe guilty in conſcience, before the Iudge haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſentence, fearing euery houre to dye for he was grieued, and in wayling ſpent the time, went talking to himſelfe, wringing of his hands, ſobbing and ſighing, he fell away from fleſh, and was very leane and kept himſelfe cloſe: neither could he abide to ſée or heare of his <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſtophiles</hi> any more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus complained that hee ſhould in his luſty time and youthfull yeares dye ſo miſerably. Chap. 59.</head>
               <p>THis ſorrowfull time drawing néere ſo troubled Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> that he began to write his minde, to the end he might peruſe it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and not forget it, and which was in manner as followeth.</p>
               <p>Ah <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> thou ſorrowfull and wofull man now muſt thou goe to the damned company in vnquenchable fire, whereas thou mighteſt haue had the ioyfull immortalitie of the ſoule, the which thou now haſt loſt. Ah groſſe vnderſtanding and wilfull will, what ſeazeth on my limbes, other then a robbing of my life? Bewaile with me my ſound and healthfull body, and wit and ſoule: bewaile with me my ſences, for you haue had your part and pleaſure aſwell as I. Oh enuy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, how haue you crept both at once into mée, and how for your ſakes, I muſt ſuffer all theſe torments! Ah whither is pitty and mercy fled? Vpon what occaſion hath heauen repayed me with this reward, by ſufferance to ſuffer me to periſh? Wherefore was I created of man? The puniſhment I ſée prepared for mée, of my ſelfe now muſt I ſuffer. Ah miſerable wretch, there is nothing in this world to ſhew mée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: then woe is me what helpeth my wailing?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="chapter">
               <head>Another complaint of Doctor Fauſtus. Chap. 60.</head>
               <p>OH poor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, wofull and weary wretch: oh ſorrowfull ſoule of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> now art thou in he number of the damned, for now muſt I waite
<pb facs="tcp:15414:38"/>for vnmeaſurable paines of death, yet farre more lamentable then euer yet any creature hath ſuffered. Ah ſenceles, wilfull, and deſperate forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes! Oh curſed and vnſtable life! O blind and careleſſe wretch, that ſo haſt abuſed thy body, ſence, and ſoule! O fooliſh pleaſure, into what a weary laborinth haſt thou brought me, blinding mine eyes in the clée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt day? Ah weake hart, Oh troubled ſoule, where is become thy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to comfort thée? Oh deſperate hope, now ſhall I neuer more be thought vpon: Oh care vpon carefulneſſe, and ſorrowes on heapes: Ah grieuous paines, that pierce my panting heart, whom is there now that can deliuer me? Would to God I knew where to hide me, or into what place to créepe or flie. Ah, woe, woe is me, be where I will, yet am I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Herewith poore <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was ſo ſorrowfully troubled, that he could not ſpeake or vtter his minde any further.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="chapter">
               <head>How Doctor Fauſtus bewailed to thinke on hell and of the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paines therein prouided for him. Chap. 61.</head>
               <p>NOw thou <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> damned wretch, how happy wert thou if as an vnreaſonable beaſt thou mighteſt die without ſoule, ſo ſholdeſt thou not fale any more doubts? But now the Deuill will take thée away both body and ſoule, and ſet thée in an vnſpeakable place of darkeneſſe: for although others ſoules haue reſt &amp; peace, yet I poore damned wretch muſt ſuffer all manner of filthy ſtench, paines, colde, hunger, thirſt, heate, fréezing, burning, hiſſing, gnaſhing and all the wrath and curſe of God, yea all the Creatures that God hath created are enemies to me. And now too late I remember that my ſpirit <hi>Mephoſtophiles</hi> did once tell mee there was great difference amongſt the damned: for the greater the ſinne the greater the torment: for as the twigs of a tree makes greater flame then the truncke thereof, and yet the truncke continueth longer in bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, euen ſo the more that a man is rooted in ſinne, the greater is his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Ah thou perpetuall damned wretch, now art thou throwne into the euerlaſting fiery lake that neuer ſhall be quenched: there muſt I dwell in all manner of wailing, ſorrow, miſery, paine, torment, griefe, howling, ſighing, ſobbing, running of eyes, ſtinking at noſe, gnaſhing of féeth, feare to the eares, horror to the conſcience, and ſhaking both of hand and foote. Ah that I could carry the heauens vpon my ſhoulders, ſo that there were time at laſt to quit me of this euerlaſting damnation: Oh who can deliuer me out of the fearefull formenting flame, the which I ſee prepared for me? Oh there is no helpe, nor any man that can deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me, nor any wailing of ſinnes can helpe me, neither is there reſt to be found for me day or night. Ah woe is me, for there is no helpe for me, no ſhield, no defence, no comfort. Where is my hold? knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:15414:39"/>dare I not truſt: and for a ſoule to God wards, that haue I not, for I ſhame to ſpeake vnto him: if I doe, no anſwere ſhall be made me, but he will hide his face from me, to the end that I ſhould not behold the ioyes of the choſen, What meane I then to complaine where no helpe is? No I know no hope reſteth in my groanings. I haue deſired that it ſhould be ſo, and God hath ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to my miſdoings: for now I muſt haue ſhame to comforme in my calamities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="chapter">
               <head>Here followeth the miſerable and lamentable end of Doctor Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, by the which all Chriſtians may take an example and warning. Chap. 62.</head>
               <p>THe full time of Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his <hi>24.</hi> yeares being come, his ſpirit appeared vnto him giuing him his writing again and commanding him to make preparation, for that the deuill would fetch him againſt a certaine time appointed. Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> mourned and ſighed wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and neuer went to bed, nor ſlept winke for ſorrow. Wherefore his ſpirit appeared againe comforting him and ſaying: My <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> be not thou ſo cowardly minded, for although that thou loſeſt thy body, it is not long vnto the day of Iudgement, and thou muſt dye at the laſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou liue many thouſand yeares. The Turks, the Iewes, and many a vnchriſtian Emperour are in the ſame condemnation: therefore my <hi>Fauſtus</hi> be of good courage, and be not diſcomforted, for the deuil hath promiſed that thou ſhalt not be in paine as the reſt of the damned are. This and ſuch like comfort he gaue him, but he tolde him falſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaying of holy Scriptures. Yet Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> that had none other expectation but to pay his debts with his owne skin, went (on the ſame day that his ſpirit ſaid the deuill would fetch him) vnto his truſty and déereſt beloued brethren and companions, as Maiſters and Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Art, and other ſtudents more, the which did often viſite him at his houſe in merriment: theſe he intreateth that they would walke into the Village called <hi>Rimlich,</hi> halfe a mile from <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and that they would there take with him for their repaſt of a ſmall banquet, the which they all agréed vnto: ſo they went together: and there held their dinner in a moſt ſumptuous manner. D. <hi>Fauſtus</hi> with them (diſſemblingly) was merry but not from the heart: wherefore he requeſted them that they would alſo take part of his rude ſupper: the which they agréed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for (quoth he) I muſt tell you what is the Victulers due: and when they ſleeped (for drinke was in their heads) then Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> paid and diſcharged the ſhot, and bound the ſtudents and the Maiſters to goe with him into another roome, for he had many wonderfull matters to
<pb facs="tcp:15414:39"/>tell them, and when they were entred the roome as he requeſted, Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſaid vnto them as hereafter followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="chapter">
               <head>An Oration of Fauſtus to the Students. Chap. 63.</head>
               <p>MY truſty and welbeloued friends, the cauſe why I haue inuited you into this place is this: Foraſmuch as you haue knowne me this many yeares in what manner of life I haue liued, practiſing all manner of Coniurations and wicked exerciſes, the which I obtained through the helpe of the deuill, into whoſe deuilliſh fellowſhip they haue brought me, the which vſe the like Art and practiſe, vrged by the deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prouocations of my fleſh, and my ſtiff-necked and rebellious will, with my filthy infernall thoughts, the which were euer before me, prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me forward ſo earneſtly, that I muſt perforce haue the conſent of the deuill to ayde me in my deuiſes. And to the end I might the better bring my purpoſe to paſſe, to haue the deuils aide and furtherance, which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue wanted in my actions, I haue promiſed vnto him at the end and accompliſhing of <hi>24.</hi> yeares, both body and ſoule, to doe therewith at his pleaſure: and this day, this diſmall day, thoſe <hi>24.</hi> yeares are fully expired, for night beginning, my houre-glaſſe is at an end, the direfull fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing whereof I carefully expect: for out of all doubt this night he will fetch me, to whome I haue giuen my ſelfe in recompence of his ſeruice, both body and ſoule, and twiſe confirmed writings with my proper blood. Now haue I called you my welbeloued Lords, friends, brethren, and fellowes, before that fatall houre, to take my friendly fare-well, to the end that my departure may not hereafter be hidden from you, beſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching you herewith (curteous louing Lords, and brethren) not to take in euill part any thing done by me, but with friendly commendations to ſalute all my friends and companions whereſoeuer, deſiring both you and them if euer I haue treſpaſſed againſt your mindes in any thing that you would heartily forgiue me: and as for thoſe lewd practiſes the which is full <hi>24.</hi> yeares I haue followed, you ſhall hereafter finde them in writing: and I beſéech you let this my lamentable end to the reſidue of your liues be a ſufficient warning that you haue God always before your eyes, praying vnto him that he would euer defend you from the temptations of the Deuill and all his falſe deceits, not falling alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from GOD, as I wretched and vngodly damned creature haue done, hauing denied and defied Baptiſme, the Sacraments of Chriſts body, God himſelfe, all heauenly powers, and earthly men: yea, I haue denyed ſuch a God that deſireth not to haue one loſt. Neither
<pb facs="tcp:15414:40"/>let the euill fellowſhip of wicked companions miſleade you as it hath done me, viſite earneſtly and oft the Church, warre and ſtriue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually againſt the Deuill with a good and ſtedfaſt beliefe in God, and Ieſus Chriſt, and vſe your vocation in holines. Laſtly, to knit vp my troubled oration, this is my friendly requeſt that you would goe to reſt, and let nothing trouble you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alſo if you chance to heare any noiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rumbling about the houſe be not therewith afraid: for there ſhall no euill happen vnto you: alſo I pray you ariſe not out of your beds. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at aboue all things I intreat you, if you hereafter find my dead earkaſſe, conuey it in the earth, for I dye both a good and bad Chriſtian, for that I knowe the deuill will haue my body, and that would I willingly giue him, ſo that he would leaue my ſoule in quiet: wherefore I pray you that you would depart to bed, and ſo I wiſh you a quiet night, which vnto mee notwithſtanding will be horrible and fearefull.</p>
               <p>This Oration or declaration was made by Doctor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> and that with a hearty and reſolute minde, to the end he might not diſcomfort them: but the Students wondred greatly thereat, that he was ſo blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for knauery, coniuration, and ſuch like fooliſh things, to giue his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule vnto the deuill, for they loued him intirely, and neuer ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected any ſuch things before he had opened his mind vnto them: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one of them ſaid vnto him: Ah friend <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> what haue you done to conceale this matter ſo long from vs? we would by the helpe of good Diuines, and the grace of God haue brought you out of this net, and haue torne you out of the bondage and chaines of Sathan, whereas now we feare it is too late, to the vtter ruine of your body and ſoule. Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> anſwered, I durſt neuer doe it, although I often minded to ſettle my ſelfe vnto godly people, to deſire counſell and helpe, and once mine olde neighbour counſelled me, that I ſhould follow his learning and leaue all my coniurations, yet when I was minded to amend, and to follow that good mans councell, then came the deuill and would haue had me away, as this night he is like to doe, and ſaid, ſo ſoone as I turned againe to God he would diſpatch me altogether. Thus euen thus, (good gentlemen and deare friends) was I inthralled in that ſata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall band, all good deſires drowned, all pitty baniſhed, all purpoſe of amendment vtterly exiled, by the tyrannous threatnings of my deadly enemie. But when the Students heard his words, they gaue him councell to doe nought elſe but call vpon God, deſiring him for the loue of his ſwéet ſon Ieſus Chriſts ſake to haue mercy vpon him, teaching him this forme of prayer: O God be mercifull vnto me, poore and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner, and enter not into iudgement with me, for no fleſh is
<pb facs="tcp:15414:40"/>able to ſtand before thée: although O Lord I muſt leaue my ſinfull bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vnto the Deuill, being by him deluded: yet thou in mercy maiſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue my ſoule.</p>
               <p>This they repeated vnto him, yet it could take no holt, but euen as <hi>Caine,</hi> he alſo ſaid his ſinnes were greater then God was able to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for all his thought was an his writing, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ant he had made it too filthy, in writing with his owne blood. The Students and the other that were there, when they had prayed for him, they wept, and ſo went foorth, but <hi>Fauſtus</hi> tarryed in the Hall: and when the Gentlemen were laid in bed, none of them could ſtéepe, for that they attended to heare if they might be priuy of his end: It hapned betwéene twelue and one a clocke at midnight, there blew a mighty ſtorme of winde againſt the houſe, as though it would haue blowne the foundation thereof out of his place. Hereupon the ſtudents began to feare, and got out of their beds comforting one another, but they would not ſtirre out of the chamber: and the Hoſt of the houſe ranne out of doores thinking the houſe would fall. The Students lay néere vnto the hall wherein Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> lay, and they heard a mighty noiſe and hiſſing, as if the hall had beene full of Snakes and Adders: with that the hall doore ſtowe open wherin doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> was, that he began to crie for help, ſaying: murther, murther, but it came foorth with halfe a voice, hollowly: ſhortly after, they heard him no more. But when it was day, the Students that had taken no reſt that night, aroſe and went into the hall, in the which they left doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> where notwithſtanding they found not <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> but all the hall lay deſprinckled with blood, his braines cleauing to the wall, for the deuill had beaten him from one wall againſt another: In one corner lay his eyes, in an other his téeth, a pittifull and fearefull ſight to behold. Then be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an the Students to waile and wéep for him, and ſought for his body in many places: laſtly they came into the yard, where they found his body lying on the horſe, dung moſt monſtrouſly torne, and fearefull to behold, for his head and all his ioynts were daſhed in péeces.</p>
               <p>The fore-named Students and Maſters that were at his death, haue obtained ſo much, that they buryed him in the village where he was ſo gréeuouſly tormented. After the which, they returned to <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and comming into the houſe of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> they found the ſeruant of <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> very ſad, vnto whome they opened all the matter, who tooke it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding heauily. There found they alſo this hiſtorie of Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> noted and of him written, as is before declared, all ſaue onely his end, the which was after by the Students thereto annexed: further, what his ſeruant had noted thereof, was made in another booke. And you haue
<pb facs="tcp:15414:41"/>heard that he held by him in his life the ſpirit of faire <hi>Helena:</hi> the which had by him one Sonne, the which he named <hi>Iuſtus Fauſtus,</hi> euen the ſame day of his death they vaniſhed away, both mother and ſonne. The houſe before was ſo darke, that ſcarfe any body could abide therein. The ſame night Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> appeared vnto his ſeruant liuely, and ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him many ſecret thinges, the which he had done and hidden in his life time. Likewiſe there were certaine which ſaw Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> looke out of the window by night as they paſſed by the houſe.</p>
               <p>And thus ended the whole hiſtorie of Doctor <hi>Fauſtus</hi> his Coniuration, and other acts that he did in his life: out of the which example euery Chriſtian may learne, but chiefly the ſtiffe-necked and high minded may thereby learne to feare God, and to be carefull of their vocation, and to be at defiance with all deuilliſh workes, as God hath moſt preciſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, to the end we ſhould not inuite the deuill as a Gueſt, nor giue him place as that wicked <hi>Fauſtus</hi> hath done: for here we haue a feareful example of his writing, promiſe, and end, that we may remember him: that we goe not aſtray, but take God alwayes before our eyes, to call a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone vpon him, and to honour him all the dayes of our life, with heart and harty prayer, and with all our ſtrength and ſoule to glorifie his holy name, defying the deuill and all his workes, to the end we may remaine with Chriſt in all endleſſe ioy: Amen, Amen: that wiſh I vnto euery Chriſtian heart, and Gods name to be glorified Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15414:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
